<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="ODD/out/GaskellDraft_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="Id_what">Diary</title>
            <author>Elizabeth Gaskell</author>
            <!-- Persistent Link to Diary: https://explore.library.leeds.ac.uk/special-collections-explore/33745 -->
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#mjk">Melissa Klamer</persName>
               <!-- Include respstmt re: photos taken, include photo files -->
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl/>
         </sourceDesc>
         <!-- commented out due to firing error re: <editionStmt>
               <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2017-08-18">August 18,
                     2017</date>. P5.</edition>
               <editor ref="mjk">Melissa J. Klamer</editor>
            </editionStmt>-->

      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="0" resp="#mjk">
               <head>Dedication</head>
               <p><persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> dedicates her
                  diary to her firstborn daughter, <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>, who was born <date when="1834-09-12">September 12,
                     1834</date>. At the time of <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>’s death, <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> was yet unmarried. She later married and had several
                  children; the diary has been handed down through <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s descendants, and is currently
                  the property of Mrs. Sarah Prince, <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s great-great granddaughter. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="dedication">
                  <pb n="1"/><p><lb/>To my dear little <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> I shall
                     <q>dedicate</q>
                  <lb/>this book, which, if I should not live to give <lb/>it her myself, will I
                  trust be reserved for her <lb/>as a token of her mother's love, and extreme
                  <lb/>anxiety in the formation of her little <lb/>daughter's character. If that
                  little daughter <lb/>should in time become a mother herself, <lb/>she may take an
                  interest in the experience <lb/>of another; and at any rate she will <lb/>perhaps
                  like to become acquainted with <lb/>her character in <choice>
                     <sic>it's</sic>
                     <reg>its</reg>
                  </choice> earliest form. I <lb/>wish that (if ever she sees this) I could
                  <lb/>give her the slightest idea of the love <lb/>and the hope that is bound up in
                  <lb/>her. The love which passeth every earth=<lb/>=ly love, and the hope that
                  however we <lb/>may be separated on earth, we may <lb/>each of us so behave while
                  sojourning here <lb/>that we may meet again to renew the <lb/>dear &amp; tender
                  tie of Mother and Daughter.</p>
               
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="1" resp="#mjk">
               <head>Entry 1</head>
               <dateline> March 10, 1835</dateline>
               <!-- Research how to structure the appropriate header information here. -->
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  6 months</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Not applicable </head>
               <head>Length of Entry: 10 handwritten pages</head>
               <p>In this first entry, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> devotes a lengthy portion of her narrative (3 full pages)
                  to writing about her own maternal choices - in this case, particularly her plans
                  for handling common parenting concerns, including bedtimes, how to respond to
                  cries and demands, and developmental milestones like learning to walk. This keen
                  awareness of motherhood is marked by self-doubt and an equally pronounced sense of
                  self-judgment stemming from Victorian assumptions about maternal duty. <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> uses the diary as a means
                  to check her own maternal behaviors, writing: <quote>though I keep laying down
                     rules, I fear I have not sufficiently attended to them, though I hope I have
                     been conscientious hitherto in discharging my duty to her.</quote> These rules
                  draw in part on educational treatises of the day; in this entry she cites a text
                  by the French authoress <persName ref="#Mme_DeSaussure">Madame Necker
                     DeSaussure</persName>. <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>’s conclusions, however, are more rigid for herself than for
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>. While insisting that
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> not be pressured into
                  walking or learning anything before she is ready, <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> repeatedly reinforces her
                  commitment to her own duty to raise <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> according to strict principles, such as telling her
                  nothing but the absolute truth and selflessly placing her own needs after those of
                  her daughter.</p>
               <p>The dedication itself, where <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> hopes the diary <quote>will be reserved for [<persName
                        ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>] as a token of her mother’s
                     love and extreme anxiety in the formation of her little daughter’s
                     character,</quote> demonstrates even at the outset the depth of introspection
                  that <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> associates
                  with the diary form, and with this manuscript in particular. Although undertaken
                  to record <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s
                     <quote>character in it’s earliest form</quote>, the diary is ostensibly also a
                  record of Gaskell’s own maternal anxieties, and in being so, it is also suggests
                  her fears of maternal mortality, which echo as an underlying theme throughout the
                  diary, both in her repeated fears of loss and in her inclusion of prayers for her
                  daughters’ safety. The brief <quote>God bless her</quote> that closes this entry
                  marks a tendency to conclude her entries with prayers for her daughters’ health
                  and safety that continues throughout the diary. At all times, the relationship
                  between mother and daughters is colored by a pervasive fear of death. </p>
               <p><persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s first entry is
                  slightly over ten handwritten pages, and was likely written on the same date as
                  the dedication; the handwriting is similar in size, saturation and ink color.
                     <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> appears to have
                  often written in the evenings when her children were in bed; this and several
                  other entries indicate <quote>evening</quote> in the dateline. <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> writes in this entry
                  about <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s bedtime routine;
                  she was laid down awake, at 6pm every evening, and since the entry concludes with
                  a comment about listening to <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s restful breathing during the time of writing, it seems
                  likely that this entry was written sometime after 6 pm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="1">
               <pb n="2"/>
               <head>
                  <date when="1835-03-10">March 10.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Tuesday
                        <time>Evening</time>. 1835.</date>
               </head>

               <p><lb/>The day after tomorrow <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>
                  will be <lb/>six months old. I wish I had begun my <lb/>little journal sooner, for
                  (though I should <lb/>have laughed at the idea twelve months <lb/>ago) there have
                  been many little indica=<lb/>=tions of disposition &amp;c. already; which I
                  <lb/>can not now remember clearly. I will <lb/>try and describe her <hi
                     rend="underline">mentally</hi>. I should <lb/>call her remarkably
                  good-tempered; though <lb/>at times she gives way to little bursts <lb/>of passion
                  or perhaps impatience would <lb/>be the right name. She is also very firm <lb/>in
                  her own little way occasionally; what <lb/>I suppose is obstinacy really, only
                  that <lb/> is so hard a word to apply to one so <lb/>dear. But in general she is
                  so good <lb/> that I feel as if I could hardly be <lb/>sufficiently thankful, that
                  the materials <lb/>put into my hands are so excellent, and
                     <pb n="3"/><lb/>beautiful. And yet it seems to increase <lb/>the responsibility. If
                  I should misguide <lb/>from carele<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sness or negligence! <choice>
                     <sic>Wilfully</sic>
                     <reg><hi rend="underline">Willfully</hi></reg>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>is not in a mother's heart. From ignorance <lb/>and errors in judgment I know
                  I may, <lb/>and probably shall, very often. But oh <persName ref="#God"
                     >Lord</persName>
                  <lb/>I pray thee to lead me right (if it be thy <lb/>will) and to preserve in me
                  the same <lb/>strong feeling of my responsibility which I <lb/>now feel. And you
                  too my dearest little <lb/>girl, if when you read this, you trace <lb/>back any
                  evil, or unhappy feeling to <lb/>my mismanagement in your childhood <lb/>forgive
                  me, love! </p>
               <p><lb/><persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> is now becoming every
                  day <lb/>more and more interesting. She looks at <lb/>and tries to take hold of
                  every thing. She <lb/>has pretty good ideas of distance and does <lb/>not try to
                  catch sunbeams now, as she <pb n="4"/>
                  <lb/>did two months ago. Her sense of sight <lb/>is much improved lately in seeing
                  objects <lb/>at a distance, and distinguishing them. <lb/>For instance I had her
                  in my arms today <lb/>in the drawing room, and her <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell"
                     >Papa</persName>
                  <lb/>was going out of the gate; and she evi=<lb break="no"/>=dently knew him;
                  smiled and kicked. <lb/>She begins to show a decided preference <lb/>to those she
                  likes; she puts out her little <lb/>arms to come to me, and would I <lb/>am sure,
                  do so to her <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName>. She catches <lb/>the
                  expression of a countenance <lb/>to which she is accustomed directly; <lb/> when
                  we laugh, she laughs; and when <lb/>I look attentive to <persName
                     ref="#Wm_Gaskell">William</persName>'s reading, <lb/>it is quite ridiculous to
                  see her little <lb/>face of gravity, and earnestness, as if <lb/>she understood
                  every word. I try always <lb/>to let her look at any thing which at=<lb break="no"
                  />=tracts her notice as long as she <unclear>will</unclear><pb n="5"/>
                  <lb/>and when I see her looking very intently <lb/>at <choice>
                     <sic>any thing</sic>
                     <reg>anything</reg>
                  </choice>, I take her to it, and let <lb/>her exercise all her senses upon
                  it-<!-- place spaces around dashes or leave words connected?-->even <lb/>to
                  tasting, if I am sure it can do her <lb/>no harm. My object is to give her a
                  <lb/>habit of fixing her attention. </p>
               <p><lb/>She takes great delight in motion just <lb/>at present; dancing, jumping,
                  shutting <lb/>and opening the hand pleases her very
                  <lb/>much.<space type="short"/><!-- long gap. Not sure whether to code this as a paragraph break or an empty space-->
                  I had no idea children <lb/>at her age, made such continued <lb/>noises; she
                  shouts, and murmurs, and <lb/>talks in her way, just like conversa=<lb break="no"
                  />=tion, varying her tones &amp;c. I wish <lb/>we could know what is passing
                  <lb/>in her little mind. She likes any=<lb break="no"/>=thing like singing, but
                  seems afraid <lb/>of the piano; today she even began <lb/>to cry, when I began to
                  play. </p><pb n="6"/>
               <p><lb/>In general, I think she is remarkably <lb/>free from fear or shyness of any
                  sort. <lb/>She goes to <choice>
                     <sic>any one</sic>
                     <reg>anyone</reg>
                  </choice> who will take her, <lb/>staring at strangers to be sure, and being
                  <lb/>very grave while they are in the room, <lb/>but not crying, or clinging to
                  me. I am <lb/>very glad of this, as though it is very <lb/>flattering and
                  endearing to me, yet <lb/>I should be sorry if she were to get the <lb/>habit of
                  refusing to go to others.</p>
               <p><lb/>Then as to her <q>bodily</q> qualifications. <lb/>She has had two teeth cut
                  with very little <lb/>trouble; but I believe the worst are <lb/>to come. She is
                  very strong in her <lb/>limbs, though because she is so fat, we <lb/>do not let
                  her use her <choice>
                     <sic>ancles</sic>
                     <reg>ankles</reg>
                  </choice> at all, <lb/>and I hope she will be rather late in <lb/>walking that her
                  little legs may be <lb/>very firm. I shall find it difficult to <lb/>damp the
                  energies of the servants in <lb/>this respect, but I intend that she shall
                  <lb/>teach herself to walk, &amp; receive no
                     assist=<!-- Tandem verification stoppped here 10/27/18 --><pb n="7"
                  /><!--photo blocks the equal sign used to mark split word or there is none here--><lb/>ance
                  from hands &amp;c. She lies down on the<lb/> floor a good deal, and kicks about;
                  a<lb/> practice I began very early, and which<lb/> has done her a great deal of
                  good.</p>
               <p><lb/>She goes to bed <hi rend="underline">awake</hi>; another practice<lb/> I began
                  early, and which is so comfort<lb break="no"/>=able I wonder it is not more
                  generally <lb/>adopted. Once or twice we have had <lb/>grand cryings, which have
                  been very <lb/>very distressing to me; but when I <lb/>have convinced myself that
                  she is not <lb/>in pain, is perfectly well, and that she <lb/>is only wanting to
                  be taken up<!-- possibly a dash between: taken-up. Consult a better image--> I
                  have <lb/>been quite firm, though I have some=<lb break="no"/>=times cried almost
                  as much as she <lb/>has. I never leave her <sic>till</sic> she is as=<lb
                     break="no"/>=leep (except in extreme cases) and as <lb/>she is put to bed at a
                  regular time <lb/>(6 o'clock) she generally gets very sleepy <pb n="8"/><lb/>while
                  being undressed. While the un=<lb break="no"/>=dre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sing is going on, I never like her <lb/>to be talked to, played with, or
                  excited <lb/>yet sometimes she is so very playful <lb/>when she ought to be put
                  down, that <lb/>a turn or two up and down the room <lb/>is required to soothe her,
                  still putting <lb/>her down awake. Sometimes she will <lb/>cry a little, and when
                  I turn her over <lb/>in her cot she fancies she is going <lb/> to be taken up and
                  is still in a moment<lb/> making the peculiar little triumphing <lb/>noise she
                  always does when she is <lb/>pleased. </p>
               <p><lb/>Crying has been a great difficulty <lb/>with me. Books do so differ. One says<lb/>
                  <quote>Do not let them have <choice>
                        <sic>any thing</sic>
                        <reg>anything</reg>
                     </choice> they <lb/>cry for</quote>, another (<persName ref="#Mme_DeSaussure"
                        >M<hi rend="superscript">me</hi> Necker de Saus<lb break="no"
                        />=sure</persName>, <title>sur L'Education Progressive</title><note resp="#mjk"><title>L’Education Progressive; ou, etude sur la cours de la vie</title> was published in England in several volumes between <date when="1829">1829</date> and <date when="1838">1838</date>. <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> must have been reading the original French; an English translation was not printed in <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName> until <date when="1838">1838</date>. <persName ref="#Mme_DeSaussure">Mme Necker de Saussure</persName> was a Swiss woman of letters known primarily for this text. The quotation included here (“les larmes des enfans sont si amère, la calme parfaite de l’âme leur est si necessaire qu’il faut surtout aparquer des larmes”) is translated “The tears of infants are so bitter, the perfect calm of the soul is so necessary to them, that it is necessary especially to prevent tears.” (Translation by Melissa Klamer, 2019) </note><!--lang="Fr"-->,
                  the <lb/>nicest <title ref="sur L'Education_Progressive"
                  >book</title><!-- bibl, rather than title here? --> I have read on the subject
                     <pb n="9"/> <lb/>says
                     <quote><!--is it possible to link this quotation to the title above?--><!--lang
                  ref="fr"-->les
                     larmes des <sic>enfans</sic> sont si a=<lb break="no"/>=mires, la calme
                     parfaite de
                     l'a&#770;me
                        <unclear unit="word" n="1"/>
                     <lb/>est si neccessaire qu'il faut surtout a<!--accent mark-->=<lb break="no"
                     />=parquer des larmes.</quote> So I had to <lb/>make a rule for myself, and
                  though <lb/>I am afraid I have not kept to it <lb/>quite as I ought, I still think
                  it a <lb/>good one. We must consider that a <lb/>cry is a child's only language
                  for <lb/>expressing its wants. It is its little way <lb/>of saying, <q>I am
                     hungry, I am very <lb/>cold,</q> and <hi rend="underline">so</hi>, I don't
                  think we should <lb/>carry out the maxim of never letting <lb/>a child have <choice>
                     <sic>any thing</sic>
                     <reg>anything</reg>
                  </choice> for crying. <lb/>If it is to have the object for which <lb/>it is
                  crying I would give it, it, <hi rend="underline">di</hi>=<lb break="no"/>=<hi
                     rend="underline">rectly</hi>, giving up any little occupation <lb/>or purpose
                  of my own, rather than <lb/>try its patience <hi rend="underline"
                     >unnecessarily</hi>. But <pb n="10"/><lb/>if it is improper for it to obtain
                  the <lb/>object, I think it right to withhold it <lb/>steadily, however much the
                  little creature <lb/>may cry. I think after one or two attempts <lb/>to conquer by
                  crying the child would
                     be<!-- no evidence of usual equal signs to mark a word broken across the line. --><lb break="no"
                  />come aware that <hi rend="underline">one</hi> cry or indication <lb/>of a want
                  was sufficient, and I think<lb/> the habit of crying would be broken. <lb/>I am
                  almost sure even my partial <lb/>adherence to this plan has prevented <lb/>many
                  crying fits with <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>. <lb/>I
                  have somewhere read that a child <lb/>gets bad habits, <hi rend="underline"
                     >first</hi>
                  <hi rend="underline">by</hi>
                  <hi rend="underline">being</hi>
                  <hi rend="underline">irritated</hi>
                  <lb/>and then by finding that crying causes <lb/>the irritation to cease. I think
                  this <lb/>is very true. I think it is the duty <lb/> of every mother to sacrifice
                  a good<lb/> deal rather than have her child <hi rend="underline">unne</hi><lb
                     break="no"/>=<hi rend="underline">cessarily</hi> irritated by <choice>
                     <sic>any thing</sic>
                     <reg>anything</reg>
                  </choice> - food <lb/>given irregularly or improperly, dress <lb/>uncomfortable,
                  even to an uneasy position. <lb/>I think this rule should be attended to <pb
                     n="11"/> <lb/>But though I keep laying down rules, I <lb/>fear I have not
                  sufficienlty attended to them, <lb/>though I hope I have been conscientious
                  <lb/>hitherto in discharging my duty to her. Still <lb/>I sometimes fear there is
                  too much pride <lb/>in my own heart in attributing her good=<lb break="no"/>=ness
                  to the success of my plans, when in <lb/>reality it is owing to her having
                  hitherto had <lb/>such good health, and freedom from pain <lb/>a ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sing for which I <choice>
                     <sic>can not</sic>
                     <reg>cannot</reg>
                  </choice> be too thank=<lb break="no"/>=ful.Still I put down <choice>
                     <sic>every thing</sic>
                     <reg>everything</reg>
                  </choice> now be=<lb break="no"/>=cause I have thought a good deal about <lb/> the
                  formation of any little plans, and I <lb/> shall like to know their success. I
                  want <lb/> to act on principles
                 <add type="metamark" place="below" cause="insertion"
                  rend="caret"/><add place="above"><hi rend="underline">now</hi></add>
                  which can be carried <lb/>on through the whole of her education. <lb/>I have
                  written a great deal tonight, and <lb/>very unconnectedly. I had no idea the
                  <lb/>journal of my own disposition, &amp; <pb n="12"/><lb/>feelings was so
                  intimately connected with <lb/>that of my little baby, whose regular brea=<lb
                     break="no"/>=thing has been the music of my thoughts <lb/>all the time I have
                  been writing. <persName ref="#God">God</persName>, <lb/>bless her. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="2" resp="#mjk">
               <head>Entry 2</head>
               <dateline>August 4, 1835</dateline>
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  11 months</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Six months since the previous entry</head>
               <head>Length of Entry: Seven handwritten pages</head>
               <p>The second entry follows the pattern <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> established at the outset of simultaneously celebrating
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s accomplishments and
                  fearing her loss. <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>
                  has carefully delineated her objectives for raising <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, many of which emphasize allowing
                  her to develop and learn at her own pace. To this end, <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> recounts that <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> recognizes many words and
                  individuals, but does not walk or talk. <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> also continues with the
                  theme of maternal responsibility, her asserting rules that she <quote>tr[ies] to
                     attend to &amp; make the servants attend to</quote>. The cheerful mood that
                  begins the entry fades as <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> reflects on an attack of croup from which <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> has recently recovered. She
                  recounts her fear of losing her daughter, which was no doubt strengthened by the
                  memory of the stillbirth of her firstborn daughter fourteen months before
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s birth. <note
                     resp="#mjk">The stillbirth occurred in <date when="1833-07">July of
                     1833</date>; at the time of this entry it had been just over two years since
                     this loss.</note> The fear is quite poignant for <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>, and she copies a portion
                  of a poem by <persName ref="#Caroline_Bowles_Southey">Caroline Bowles</persName>,
                     <quote>To A Dying Infant</quote>, which was frequently used as a Victorian
                  epitaph. The entry includes a prayer of thankfulness that <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> was spared, which falls in this
                  case mid-entry. </p>
               <p>This is the only entry in the diary to have a significant portion of the text
                  missing. The top third of the second page has been removed, presumably cut because
                  the edge of the remaining page is smooth. The second page [recto] shows marks
                  where a small 2-3 fragment of the page is still attached to the binding of the
                  codex. Given the typical spacing of <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>’s handwritten lines, her habit of noting words broken
                  across the lines with equal signs, and the number and placement of the extant
                  marks on the fragment, we can assume that approximately six lines of text are
                  missing on the recto side of the page, and 5-6 lines on the verso. We can surmise
                  that the all of the text on the surrounding pages, together with the section that
                  remains from the lower section of the page, are all fragments of the second diary
                  entry, and that the lost sections did not include the start or endpoint of another
                  diary entry. This is clear because the following (third) entry, dated <date
                     when="1835-10-04">October fourth 1835</date>, begins, <quote>I see it is
                     exactly two months since I last wrote in this book,</quote> which indicates
                  that this second entry, dated <date when="1835-08-04">August 4th</date>, is the
                  one immediately preceding it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="2">
               <head>
                  <date when="1835-08-04">August 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Tuesday <time>Evening</time>. 1835.</date>
               </head>
               <p><lb/>It seems a very long time since I have<lb/> written anything about my little
                  darling,<!--code other names for Marianne, like this one?--><!-- ENDED HERE, 9/25/17 - line 3 of second entry. resp#mjk--><lb/>
                  and I feel as if I had been negligent<lb/> about it, only it is so difficult to know<lb/>
                  <!-- double check these first two "wheres" - could be "when" instead-->where to
                  begin or where to stop when talking<lb/> thinking or writing about her.</p>
               <p><lb/>In a few days she will be eleven months<lb/> old; and in some things I suppose she
                  is<lb/> rather backward; in walking and talking<lb/> for instance. <hi
                     rend="underline">I</hi> fancy she says <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Mama</persName>,<lb/> but I think it is only
                  fancy. She can<lb/> stand pretty steadily, taking hold of some=<lb break="no"
                  />=thing, for a few minutes and then she <lb/>pops down. But as I am not very<lb/>
                  anxious for her to walk or talk earlier <pb n="13"/><lb/>than her nature prompts,
                  and as her <lb/> Papa thinks the same, we allow her to <lb/>take her own
                  way.</p>
               <p><lb/>She has various little accomplishments <lb/>of her own, clapping hands,
                  shaking<lb/> hands, which are very pretty, though I <lb/>sometimes fear we rather
                  try to <lb/>make her exhibit too much to strangers. We <lb/>must take care of this
                  as she grows older. <lb/>She understands many words &amp; sentences <lb/><q>Where
                     are the cows</q>, <q>the flies</q> &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c. <lb/>I am very much
                  afraid of her catch=<lb break="no"/>=ing cro<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s or angry expre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sions of countenance<lb/> or even one that is not quite happy - <lb/>I
                  find her own changes so directly <lb/>to the expre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sion she sees. If <del rend="strikethrough">we</del><add place="inline"
                     >I</add> could <lb/>but consider a child properly, what <lb/>a beautiful safe-guard from
                  evil would <lb/><choice>
                     <sic>it's</sic>
                     <reg>its</reg>
                  </choice>presence be. Oh! I do hope &amp; intend </p>
               <pb facs="page-image.png" n="14"/><!--2020-03-02 ebb: I'm just planting a sample @facs attribute here for us to transform.
               Optimally: we'll be able to write an XSLT identity transformation that plugs in your @facs attribute values 
               based on their regularly named filenames and URL (site addresses). Jeffrey C. Witt is the member of the IIIF community who I know works
               with XML and IIIF, and he will know how this is best done.  
               -->
               <gap unit="lines" quantity="6"/><note resp="#mjk">The top third of the second leaf of this entry has been cut away. See headnote for this entry.</note>
               <p><lb/>how all a woman's life, at least so it <lb/>seems to me now, ought to have a
                  refe=<lb break="no"/>=rence to the period when she will be
                  ful=<lb break="no"/>=filling one of her greatest &amp; highest<lb/> duties, those
                  of a mother. I feel myself<lb/> so unknowing, so doubtful about many<lb/> things
                  in her intellectual &amp; moral <lb/>treatment already, and what shall I<lb/> be when
                  she grows older, &amp; asks those<lb/> puzzling qustions that children do?<lb/> I
                  hope I<!--unclear marking near I--> shall always preserve my <lb/>present good
                  intentions &amp; sense of my<lb/> holy trust, and then I must pray, to be<lb/>
                  forgiven for my errors, &amp; led into a better<lb/> course.</p>
               <pb n="15"/>
               <p><gap unit="lines" quantity="6"
                  ><!--quantity unknown here, back of gap margin is not visible--></gap><note resp="#mjk">The top third of the second leaf of this entry has been cut away. See headnote for this entry.</note><lb/>afraid of
                  pleasure being a<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sociated with<lb/> the faces of pain they pull. Perhaps this<lb/> is
                  foolish but I will put every thing down<lb/> relating to her.</p>
               <p><lb/>She has been to <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName><note resp="#mjk"><placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName> was the home of the Hollands, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Holland_Stevenson">mother</persName>’s family. After <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Holland_Stevenson">Elizabeth (Holland) Stevenson</persName> died when young <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Elizabeth</persName> was thirteen months old, she went to <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName> to live with her <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Holland_Stevenson">mother</persName>’s <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">sister</persName>, <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Hannah (Holland) Lumb</persName> and her daughter, <persName ref="#Marianne_Lumb">Marianne Lumb</persName>. </note> and
                     <placeName ref="#Warrington">Warring<lb/>ton</placeName><note resp="#mjk"><placeName ref="#Warrington">Warrington</placeName> was the home of <persName ref="#William_Gaskell_Senior">William Gaskell</persName>’s family, who were Dissenters. His widowed <persName ref="#Margaret_Gaskell_Dimock">mother</persName> lived there with her second husband, <persName ref="#Edward_Dimock">Edward Dimock</persName>, who was also a Unitarian minister at <placeName ref="#Sankey-Street-Chapel">Sankey Street Chapel</placeName> in <placeName ref="#Warrington">Warrington</placeName>Warrington. </note> since I last wrote in this journal.<lb/>
                  And oh! after her visit to <placeName ref="#Warrington">Warrington</placeName><lb/> she was very
                  very ill; and I was very<lb/> much afraid we should have lost her.<lb/> I did so
                  try to be resigned; but I cannot<lb/> tell how I sickened at my heart, at<lb/> the
                  thought of seeing her no more here.<lb/><quote type="unattributed">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Her empty crib to see</l>
                        <l>Her silent nursery,</l>
                        <l>Once gladsome with her mirth</l>
                     </lg></quote></p>
               <pb n="16"/>
               <p><lb/>I am sometimes afraid of using expre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sions<lb/> of gratitude to <persName ref="#God">God</persName>, for fear
                  I should get<lb/> into the habit of using them without<lb/> sufficiently feeling
                  them, but I think there<lb/> is no danger when I say that <!--prayer here-->I ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s &amp; thank<lb/> my <persName ref="#God">Father</persName>, &amp; hers,
                  for not taking away the<lb/> ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sing he gave; and oh! may I not make<lb/>her into an idol, but strive to
                  prepare both<lb/> her &amp; myself for the change that may<lb/> come any
                  day.</p>
               <p><lb/>After her illne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s her temper had suffered<lb/> from the indulgence that was nece<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sary<lb/> during her illne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s; but as she grew strong<lb/> it wore away, and I think she is
                  now<lb/>as sweet-tempered as ever in general; though<lb/>at times her little pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sions are terrible<lb/>and give me quite a heavy heart.</p>
               <p><lb/>I should say impatience will be one<lb/> of her greatest faults; and I scarecely<lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <sic>knows</sic>
                     <reg>know</reg>
                  </choice> the best way of managing it.<lb/> I certainly think being calm oneself
                  &amp;<lb/> showing that her impatience makes<pb n="17"/> <lb/>no difference in the quickne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s or slowne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s<lb/> of her actions, and never disappointing<lb/> her when <hi
                     rend="underline">unnece<choice>
                        <sic>&#383;</sic>
                        <reg>s</reg>
                     </choice>sary</hi> are good rules; <lb/>but then in every little case it is so
                  diffi<lb break="no"/>=cult for an undecided person like me to<lb/> determine at once, and
                  yet <hi rend="underline">every</hi>
                  <hi rend="underline">body</hi><lb/> &amp; every book says that decision is of<lb/>
                  such consequence to the comfort &amp; conse=<lb/>=quently to the temper of a
                  child; &amp; that<lb/> it is almost better for <hi rend="underline">the</hi>
                  <hi rend="underline">time</hi>, to go<lb/> on with a treatment that is <hi
                     rend="underline">not</hi>
                  <hi rend="underline">bad</hi>,<lb/> rather than by changing to a better, let<lb/>
                  the child see your wavering. I only<lb/> mean for the time. I must take care<lb/>
                  to have presence of mind to remark<lb/> &amp; adopt the better method every
                  future<lb/> occasion.</p>
               <p><lb/>There is another thing I try to attend to<lb/> &amp; make the servants attend to;
                     never<pb n="18"/> <lb/>by way of distracting her attention to call<lb/> it to a
                  thing that is not there, and never<lb/> to promise her any thing
                  unconditionally<lb/> without performing it.</p>
               <p><lb/>Of course she now knows all those whom<lb/> she is in the habit of seeing. I do
                  not<lb/> think she is remarkably shy, although<lb/> more so than she was. But
                  certainly<lb/> most people take children in such a<lb/> brusque injudicious
                  mannter that no<lb/> wonder they are often shy.</p>
               <p><lb/>And now I shall conclude tonight, &amp;<lb/> I do not intend to be so long
                  again<lb/> without writing about my dear little<lb/> girl.</p>
               <pb n="19"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="3">
               <head>Entry 3</head>
               <dateline> October 4, 1835</dateline>
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  13 months</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Two months since previous entry</head>
               <head>Length of Entry: </head>
               <p>At the time she wrote this entry, <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> was the same age that <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> herself had been when she
                  lost her own mother. The entry is preoccupied with <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s observations and
                  decisions related to <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s
                  physical health. She introduces her belief that in children, <quote>every change
                     of temper might be deduced from some corresponding change in the body.</quote>
                  She cites <persName ref="#Andrew_Combe">Combe</persName>’s
                     <title>Physiology</title> as one source of this conviction and describes in
                  detail <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s temperament. In
                  addition to offering examples of <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s <quote>self-government</quote> and her improvement in
                  patience, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> also
                  lays out again her mother-rules for raising <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>. Due to <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s fragility, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> plans to dress her warmly and keep her indoors during the
                  winter, and she has stopped feeding <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> milk, believing that thickened broth is a more
                     <quote>strengthening</quote> food. The entry concludes with a lengthy prayer
                  asking not only for <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s
                  health, but for <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s
                  own strength in the event that she should lose her only daughter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="3">
               <head>
                  <date when="1835-10-04">Sunday <time>Evening</time>
                     <unclear unit="word" n="1"/> October 4 1835</date>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <lb/>I see it is exactly two months since I <lb/>last wrote in this book, and I
                  hope <lb/>my little girl is improved both in <lb/><q>body &amp; mind</q> since then. She suffers <lb/>a good deal from the changes
                  of wea=<lb break="no"/>=ther we have had, and I have found <lb/>it nece<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sary to leave off milk as an <lb/>article of diet at present. She lives
                  on <lb/>broth thickened with arrowroot, &amp; <lb/>I think this food strengthens
                  her, but <lb/>she is still a delicate child, and back=<lb/>=ward in
                  walking. I hope she will <lb/>not be hurried by <choice><sic>any one</sic><reg>anyone</reg></choice> in her <lb/>attempts at
                  trotting about, for the more <lb/>I see and hear of children the more <lb/>I am
                  convinced that when they <lb/>feel their limbs strong enough to <lb/>begin to walk
                  they will constantly <lb/>be trying their powers, &amp; that till <pb n="20"/>
                  <lb/>nature prompts this, it is worse than <lb/>usele<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s to force them to their feet.</p>
               <p><lb/>She is I believe a small child of her <lb/>age, though tall, and she has
                  looked <lb/>(&amp; been too, alas!) very delicate since <lb/>that sad, sad illne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s in the summer. <lb/>I am going to clothe her in flannel <lb/>waistcoats, and long sleeves to her frocks<lb/> this winter, and to keep her in
                     <hi rend="underline">well</hi>=<lb break="no"/>=<hi rend="underline">aired</hi> rooms in
                  preference to going <lb/>much out of doors unle<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s the weather <lb/>is very tempting. She has now had <lb/>eight teeth for
                  some time, and is <lb/>about some more I fancy; perhaps <lb/>when her teeth are
                  all through her <lb/>health may be stronger. Oh may I<lb/> try not to fasten &amp; <choice>
                     <sic>centre</sic>
                     <reg>center</reg>
                  </choice> my affections <lb/>too strongly on such a frail little <lb/>treasure,
                  but all my anxiety though <lb/>it renders me so aware of her fragility <lb/>of
                  life makes me cling daily more &amp; <lb/>more to her. </p>
               <pb n="21"/>
               <p><lb/>I think her disposition has im=<lb break="no"/>=proved since I
                  wrote last; she is <lb/>not so impatient(perhaps it was <lb/>the remains of her
                  former illne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s.) <lb/>she does not throw herself back in <lb/>the pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sionate way way she used to do <lb/>seven or eight weeks ago, and
                  she <lb/>bears her little disappointments better. <lb/>The fewer she can have of
                  these, &amp; the better <lb/>I think, and I try to avoid
                  exci=<lb break="no"/>=ting her expectations, even when they <lb/>are pretty certain of being gratified, <lb/>for the excitement (which is
                  always <lb/>so great in a child) is injurious, &amp; <lb/>produces a degree of
                  impatience. <lb/>There are &amp; always will be <choice>
                     <sic>enow</sic>
                     <reg>enough</reg>
                  </choice> of disap=<lb break="no"/>=pointments to enure a
                  child to bearing <lb/>them, and they will encrease with <lb/>years and with the
                  power of enduring, <lb/>&amp; what I mean to say is that all that <pb n="22"/>
                  <lb/>can be averted by a little fore-thought <lb/>on the part of the parent or nurse,
                  with=<lb break="no"/>out interfering with the nece<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sary degree <lb/>of quiet but resolute discipline, should <lb/>be
                  attended to and removed. I do not <lb/>like the plan in fashion formerly, of <hi
                     rend="underline">ma</hi>=<lb break="no"/>=<hi rend="underline">king</hi> trials for young children; there will <lb/>naturally be some which the child must <lb/>bear, and the parent calmly witne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s, but <lb/>creating disappointments on purpose to <lb/>enure the poor
                  little things to them in <lb/>after-life seems like giving them rich <lb/>unsuitable food, which grown up people <lb/>may &amp; do eat, but which their
                  delicate <lb/>stomachs cannot yet digest. When <lb/>young their feelings,
                  especially those un=<lb break="no"/>=der the direct control of the senses are <lb/>so acute,
                  which the powers which will <lb/>eventually it is to be hoped, control their <lb/>feelings are in a dormant state. <lb/>It is quite astonishing to see the
                  diffe=<lb break="no"/>rence bodily feelings make in
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Mari=<lb break="no"/>=anne</persName>'s temper &amp;
                  powers of enducance.<!-- manuscript check... punctuation missing here--><pb
                     n="23"/> <lb/>I was in a great measure prepared for this <lb/>by <persName
                     ref="#Andrew_Combe">Combe</persName>'s <title>Physiology</title>, but I had no
                  idea how <lb/>every change of temper might be deduced <lb/>from some corresponding
                  change in the body. <lb/>Mothers are sometimes laughed at for
                  attri=<lb break="no"/>=buting little freaks of temper to
                  teething &amp;c. <lb/>but I don't think those who laugh at them <lb/>(I used to be
                  one) have had much to do <lb/>with children. I do not mean to say that <lb/>the
                  habit of self control may not be given <lb/>and that at a very early age, but I
                  think <lb/>that with certain states of the body, feelings <lb/>will exist which
                     <hi rend="underline">ought</hi> to be controlled, <lb/>and that every thing
                  physical tending <lb/>to produce those peculiar states of the body <lb/>should be
                  avoided, with as much care as <lb/>we would avoid anything moral tending <lb/>to
                  produce moral will. I wish I could <lb/>act more upon this conviction myself; <lb/>want of sleep invariably brings on an irritable <lb/>state of excitement; and want
                  of food, <lb/>though I may not have the sensation of <lb/>hunger, has in general
                  the same effect. <pb n="24"/><lb/>I should describe <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> as a child <lb/>with whom
                  excitement should be particularly <lb/>avoided; and yet it is a very tempting <lb/>thing to see the little cheek flush, &amp; the eye <lb/>dilate, and the childish
                  lip look so eloquent. </p>
               <p><lb/>She is very much tired &amp; consequently more <lb/>irritable after a certain
                  degree of play, &amp; <unclear unit="word" quantity="1"><supplied resp="#Wilson">novelty</supplied></unclear><lb/> and besides her
                  sensibilities seem to me very <lb/>acute. If she sees others laughing when she
                  is <lb/>grave &amp; serious, or is not aware of the joke; she <lb/>bursts into
                  tears; I fancy it must a want <lb/>of sympathy with her (at the time) serious <lb/>&amp; thoughtful feelings which makes her cry, <lb/>but it must be a morbid
                  feeling I should <lb/>think, &amp; one that for her happine<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s had <lb/>better be checked, <hi rend="underline">if I but knew
                  how</hi>. <lb/>Then unexpected pleasure has occasionally <lb/>made her cry; seeing
                  her <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName> after an <lb/>absence of a few
                  days; and I thought tears <lb/>were not a common manifestation of joy <lb/>in
                  children (so young, not 13 months old yet.<supplied resp="#mjk">)</supplied> <lb/>I feel very ignorant of the best
                  way of ma=<lb break="no"/>=naging their sensibilities, so
                  beautiful when <lb/>healthy, &amp; so distre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sing when morbid. <pb n="25"/> <lb/>Perhaps as her body becomes stronger,
                  her mind <lb/>will too. There is a laugh of hers which is
                  al=<lb break="no"/>=most sure to end in a cry. She is in
                  general <lb/>very gentle, rather grave especially with
                  stran=<lb break="no"/>=gers, and remarkably observing,
                  watching <lb/>actions, things &amp;c. with such continued attention. <lb/>She is
                  very <hi rend="underline">feminine</hi> I think in her quietne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s <lb/>which is as far removed from inactivity of <lb/>mind as possible.
                  She sits on the ground <lb/>much more than she did, amusing herself<lb/> pretty
                  well(this amusing <hi rend="underline">herself</hi>, has been <lb/>I fear more my
                  theory than my practice, <lb/>otherwise she would try longer to reach <lb/>her
                  <choice><sic>play things</sic><reg>playthings</reg></choice> herself &amp;c., but this <hi rend="underline">may be</hi> <lb/>bodily
                  inability.</p>
               <p><lb/>Her accomplishments are numerous <lb/>and varied;- barking like a dog, meowing, <lb/>
                  <hi rend="underline">in a way</hi>, ki<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sing, pointing to various <lb/>articles when named &amp;c &amp;c
                  &amp;c.</p>
               <p><lb/><persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">William</persName> told me the other day I was
                  not <lb/>of a jealous disposition; I do not think <pb n="26"/> <lb/>he knows me; in
                  general <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> prefers <lb/>being
                  with me I hope &amp; think, yet at times <lb/>she shows a marked preference for
                     <persName ref="#Betsy_household">Betsy</persName>, <lb/>who has always been as
                  far as I can judge <lb/>a kind, judicious, and tender nurse.
                  To<lb break="no"/>=night <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> was sadly tired, and I <lb/>would fain have care<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sed &amp; soothed her while <lb/><persName ref="#Betsy_household">Betsy</persName> was performing various little
                  offices for <lb/>her on her knee, and <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >M.A.</persName> absolutely pushed <lb/>me away, fearing I should take her.
                  This was <lb/>hard to bear; but I am almost sure I have <lb/>never shown this
                  feeling to any one; for I <lb/>believe <persName ref="#Betsy_household"
                     >Betsy</persName> fully deserves and returns her <lb/>love, &amp; having more
                  bodily strength can amuse <lb/>her
                  more than I can in <!-- word is blurred by a small ink blot behind the n. --> different ways. <lb/>There will come a
                  time when she will know <lb/>how a mother's love exceeds all others; &amp; <lb/>meanwhile, I will try never to put myself in <lb/>rivalry with another for my
                  child's affections <lb/>but to encourage every good &amp; grateful feeling <lb/>on her part towards every one; and particularly<lb/> towards a faithful &amp;
                  affectionate servant. <lb/>I have been much gratified these few <lb/>days past by
                  the beginning of self restraint <pb n="27"/> <lb/>in the little creature; she has
                  sometimes <lb/>been washed in water either too hot or too <lb/>cold, and taken a
                  dislike to it. this week <lb/>past I have in general got up to wash <lb/>her
                  myself, or see by the thermometer that <lb/>the water was the right heat (from 85
                  to 90.) <lb/>and <persName ref="#Betsy_household">Betsy</persName>, and I have
                  tried to distract her <lb/>attention &amp; prevent her crying; this last two <lb/>days she has tried hard to prevent herself <lb/>from crying, giving gulps &amp;
                  strains to keep <lb/>it down. Oh may this indeed be the
                  begin=<lb break="no"/>=ning of self government!</p>
               <p><lb/><persName ref="#God">Lord</persName>! Unto thee do I commit this darling <lb/>precious treasure; thou knowest how
                  I love <lb/>her; I pray that I may not make her too <lb/>much my idol, and oh! if
                  thoug shouldst <lb/>call her away from <quote>the evil to come</quote> may <lb/>I try to yield
                  her up to him who gave her <lb/>to me without a murmur - I hope I may <lb/>say
                  thou also knowest how truly I wish to <lb/>do my duty to her; Help my ignorance.
                  O <persName ref="#God">Lord</persName> <lb/>strengthen my good purposes, &amp; preserve <pb n="28"/><lb/>a due
                  sense of my holy trust, which I now <lb/>acknowledge with fear &amp; trembling;
                  And yet <lb/>if I do right in endeavouring, thou <persName ref="#God">Lord</persName> <lb/>will ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s me and her, and lead her right <lb/>at last, and forgive her <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">mother</persName>'s errors. I pray <lb/>thee to ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s her through our Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="4">
               <head>Entry 4</head>
               <dateline>December 28, 1835</dateline>
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  15 months</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Two and a half months since the previous entry.</head>
               <head>Length of Entry: Six handwritten pages</head>
               <p><persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> continues
                  describing <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s development
                  and her own convictions about parenting in this entry. According to the
                  descriptions given here, the Gaskells were still calling <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>
                  <quote>baby</quote>. She would be an only child until 1837. <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> both celebrates behaviors
                  that she interprets as the beginning of self-government, while also commenting at
                  length on <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s recovery from
                  an illness that is recounted in the previous entry. She mentions throughout
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s personality- that she
                  recognizes family, will share food, rarely cries, etc., and mentions her growing
                  vocabulary and general observation and attentiveness. Throughout the entry, in
                  addition to learning more about <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> - she still does not walk, and is still living on
                  thickened broth, which <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> believes has improved her health - we continue to learn
                  more about <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s
                  maternal instincts. She is deeply self-critical and sets high standards for
                  herself. In the opening of the entry, she criticizes herself for not having
                  written sooner, although it has been only two months since the previous entry. She
                  also claims that she <quote>ought not</quote> to be negligent in any regard toward
                  her daughter, including in this instance, in writing about her in the journal. Of
                  particular note in this entry is the penultimate sentence, in which <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> writes, <quote>I feel
                     weak &amp; exhausted with writing, or I had meant to write more.</quote> This
                  admission, in addition to underscoring the duty <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> feels to keep the diary,
                  foregrounds the weight which maternal writing held for <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>. This writing is not
                  merely record keeping or reflection; it is a deeply personal, emotionally invested
                  act which requires energy of the author. Even paper motherhood is taxing. The
                  entry, as many do, ends with a prayer, asking a blessing upon <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, and help for <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> as she fulfils her sense
                  of duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="4">
               <head>
                  <date when="1835-12-28">Monday <time>Evening</time> Dec<add place="above">r</add>.
                     28. 1835.</date>
               </head>
               <p><lb/>My darling little girl! How long it is <lb/>since I wrote about you. But I
                  have been <lb/>ill, and perhaps lazy, which I certainly <lb/>ought not to be in
                  anything concerning you.</p>
               <p><lb/>
                  <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> is much stronger I trust
                  <lb/>than when I wrote last, but she has
                  re=<!--word breaks across the line --><lb/>=quired a great deal of care, &amp;
                  very <lb/>nourishing food; isingla<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s di<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>solved in <lb/>broth &amp;c.
                  <!-- unclear - ampersand before this word? seems to blend into the following.-->With
                  her strength has her <lb/>good temper returned, which is in ac=<lb/>=cordance with
                  my theory that when <lb/>children at any rate, are irritable some=<lb/>thing is
                  physically the matter with <lb/><pb n="29"/> <lb/>them. When she does become angry now,
                  she <lb/> is easily calmed, and we have begun to try <lb/> and make her show
                  sorrow - it can be <lb/> but showing at present; but when she has <lb/> been
                  angry, we look grave, <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
                  <hi rend="underline">angry</hi>, &amp; <lb/>sometimes put our<unclear
                     reason="illegible" unit="chars" quantity="1"/> hands before our <lb/> faces,
                  which always attracts her attention, <lb/>&amp; by so doing stops her little pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sion. <lb/>She tries to <!--check this word-->pull in down, &amp; I
                  generally <lb/> ask her <q>is Baby sorry for having been <lb/> impatient
                     &amp;c.;</q> which she quite under=<lb/>=stands, and in general makes her
                  little <lb/> a<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>senting noise, &amp; ki<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>ses me. She quite <lb/>understands me when I gently tell <lb/>her to be
                  patient about anything <!--punctuation mark here?-->
                  <q>Wait <lb/>a little bit dear little Baby; <persName ref="#Betsy_household"
                        >Betsy</persName> will <lb/>come down,</q> always makes her still;
                  <lb/>because for one thing, I have never <lb/>allowed her to be told any one was
                  <lb/>going to do anything for her, unle<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s <pb n="30"/>
                  <lb/>they <hi rend="underline">really</hi> were, and have tried to <lb/>speak as
                     <hi rend="underline">truly</hi> to her as ever I could - <lb/>If before
                     <persName ref="#Betsy_household">Betsy</persName> comes with her dinner-
                  <lb/>or whatever she wants, she again becomes <lb/>fidgety I again ask her to
                  wait, and <lb/>show her something to amuse her.</p>
               <p><lb/>She is not greedy though often very <lb/>hungry; but I think at any time she
                  <lb/>likes us to have a piece, or a spoonful <lb/>of whatever she is having,
                  provided we <lb/>do not take it out of her hand, which <lb/>we do not attempt to
                  do, as a truthful <lb/>spirit on her part can not be made <lb/>by violence, but
                  will come naturally <lb/>when she sees that we are scrupulous <lb/>in respecting
                  her little rights.</p>
               <pb n="31"/>
               <p><lb/>A few weeks ago her <persName ref="#Margaret_Gaskell_Dimock">grandmama</persName>
                  sent <lb/>her some sweet biscuits, and at first <lb/>I feared she was inclined to
                  be selfish <lb/>with these luxuries, for she had never tasted <lb/>anything sweet
                  before. She refused occasion=<lb/>=ally when we asked for a bit, instead of
                  <lb/>offering with her own accord, but it wore off <lb/>and now she gives as
                  freely as ever.</p>
               <p><lb/>She is remarkably good in being content <lb/>with a refusal, if we do not
                  think any <lb/>Eatable proper for her. She ki<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>ses, &amp; points &amp; <lb/>tries to speak, but does not cry when we
                  <lb/>say no. I speak in general for of course <lb/>there are times when she is not so
                  good. <lb/>Her greatest naughtine<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s is in being washed <lb/>&amp; dre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sed. She cries sadly over the washing <lb/>which I think must be owing to
                  her <lb/>having been put in <add place="above">it<metamark place="below"
                     function="insertion" rend="caret"/></add> too cold sometimes. <lb/>She
                  dislikes <hi rend="underline">finishing</hi> her food, and by <lb/><unclear
                     unit="character" quantity="1"><supplied resp="#mjk">a</supplied></unclear>
                  curious sort of fancy, often refuses <pb n="32"/><lb/>the last two or three
                  spoonsful through <lb/>dread of coming to the bottom.</p>
               <p><lb/>I am rather afraid from being the only <lb/>child, she is a little too
                  dependent on <lb/>others, for instance if when sitting on <lb/>the floor a
                  plaything rolls away, she has <lb/>no idea of scrambling after it, but looks
                  <lb/>up beseechingly for some one to help her. <lb/>To be sure she is very weak in
                  her limbs <lb/>scarcely attempting to walk with two <lb/>hands, though nearly 16
                  months.</p>
               <p><lb/>She is extremely fond of her <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName>,
                  shouting <lb/>out his name whenever she hears his <lb/>footsteps, never mistaking
                  it, and dancing <lb/>with delight when she hears the bell which <lb/>is a signal
                  for her to come in after din=<lb/>=ner.</p>
               <p><lb/>She will talk before she walks I think- <lb/>She can say pretty plainly
                        <q><persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName>, dark <lb/><!--unsure-->stir,
                     ship, lamp, book, tea, sweep</q> &amp;c. - <lb/>leaving poor <hi
                     rend="underline"><persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Mama</persName></hi> in the back ground. <lb/>She is delighted when we stir
                  the fire or <pb n="33"/><lb/>make any <hi rend="underline">commotion</hi> in the
                  room. <lb/>I am sometimes surprised to find <lb/>how she understands, &amp; tries
                  to understand <lb/>what we say amongst ourselves.</p>
               <p><lb/>For instance, I was one day speaking of <lb/><hi rend="underline"
                     >biscuits</hi>, but fearing if she understood <lb/>me, her mopes would be
                  excited, I <lb/>merely described them as <q>things that <lb/>were on the breakfast
                     table this morning</q>. <lb/>(there were
                     none<!-- this incorrect notation - the word is "in", and it is legible albeit underneath what appears to be a blot of ink--><unclear
                     reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"><supplied resp="#mjk"
                     >in</supplied></unclear> the room at the time, <lb/>when immediately she began
                  to dance <lb/>in <persName ref="#Fanny_household">Fanny</persName>'s arms saying
                  Bis, bis, bis.</p>
               <p><lb/>She is I think a small child, &amp; I fear <lb/>not a very strong one. We
                  hope to <lb/>take <sic>to</sic> her to the sea-side this spring.</p>
               <p><lb/><!--insert prayer element here-->Oh may I constantly bear in mind <lb/>the words
                     <quote>The <persName ref="#God">Lord</persName> hath given, &amp; the
                        <lb/><persName ref="#God">Lord</persName> hath taken away. Ble<choice>
                        <sic>&#383;</sic>
                        <reg>s</reg>
                     </choice>sed be the <lb/>name of the <persName ref="#God"
                     >Lord</persName>.</quote> I feel weak &amp; <pb n="34"/><lb/>exhausted with
                  writing, or I had <lb/>meant to write more. <persName ref="#God">God</persName>
                  help my <lb/>dearest child, and help her mother in <lb/>her earnest
                  endeavours.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="5">
               <head> Entry 5</head>
               <dateline>February 7, 1836</dateline>
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  17 months</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Five weeks since the previous entry</head>
               <head>Length of Entry: Nearly six handwritten pages</head>
               <p>Although this is not the last entry in which <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> writes only about
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, it is the last one in
                  which she has only one child. By the date of the following entry, <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> was already expecting her
                  second daughter, <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Margaret Emily (called Meta)
                  </persName>. Six of the eleven journal entries, including this one, are written on
                  Sundays, usually in the evenings. <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> opens this entry with a recollection of the sermon text,
                  drawn from the Christmas narrative in <bibl>Luke</bibl>, which mentions a mother
                  treasuring memory of her son <note>See textual note regarding the placement of
                     this reading in February</note>. <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> connects the text with her own maternal practice of
                  actively seeking to remember her children, and specifically credits her
                  diary-keeping practice: <quote>I sometimes think I may find this little journal a
                     great help in recalling the memory of my darling child if we should lose
                     her.</quote></p>
               <p>After this rather melancholy opening, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> goes on to record <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s development according to her custom: first physical
                  development, and then social and emotional. Between the lines of the text,
                  however, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> has
                  inscribed another record, the record of her own re-reading of the journal. Beyond
                  merely suggesting that rereading the journal <quote>would</quote> be helpful in
                  the instance of <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s death,
                  Gaskell actually rereads her diary while she is living, as indicated by the
                  sentence, <quote>I see I have generally begun my journal with describing the
                     bodily progress she has made, and I will keep to the proper order of
                     things.</quote> Thus, even in writing the diary itself, <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> is prescribing and
                  following maternal rules. The diary too, must follow a carefully planned form in
                  order to be successful. It must be <quote>proper</quote>.</p>
               <p><persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> is on the whole
                  pleased with <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s development
                  here, claiming that her personality promises to be affectionate and pleasant,
                  although she bemoans her disobedience. The remaining diary entry emphasizes
                  obedience on two levels: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s
                  disobedience in trying to traverse a gap between two chairs, resulting in a fall,
                  and <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s own
                  disobedience to her perceived higher calling as a mother. <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> ends this entry with a
                  rather lengthy prayer element, in which she bemoans the <quote>sin that doth so
                     easily beset me,</quote> anger, as the rest of the entry would suggest, and
                  prays for help to control herself, particularly for her daughter. She “intends”
                  herself to be patient, just as she <quote>intends</quote>
                  <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> to be independent, and as
                  in much of the journal, she takes the responsibility herself, though calling on a
                  higher power to support her goals. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="5">
               <head>
                  <date when="1836-02-07">Feb<add place="above"><hi rend="underline">ry</hi></add>
                        7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.
                     1836.<!-- how to code the superscript th with the period below?--></date>
               </head>
               <note resp="#mjk">The first extant letter contemporaneous to the diary occurs between
                  these entries, dated <date when="1836-05-12">May 12, 1836</date>; it was written
                  to <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Gaskell_Holland">Elizabeth Gaskell</persName>, her
                  sister-in-law, from Sandlebridge, a home of <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>'s Holland relatives. The
                  letter mentions that <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> had been reading Wordsworth at the time.</note>
               <p><lb/>This morning we heard a sermon from <lb/>the text <quote>And his mother kept all
                     these <lb/>sayings in her heart.</quote> Oh! how very, very <lb/>true it is -
                  and I sometimes think I may <lb/>find this little
                  <!--insert reference to journal itself, some sort of listbibl?-->journal a great
                  help in <lb/>recalling the memory of my darling child, <lb/>if we should lose
                  her.</p>
               <p><lb/>We have had much cause for thankfulne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s <lb/>since I wrote last; she has daily improved <lb/>in health, and I
                  think her character has <lb/>developed itself a good deal latterly, and
                  <lb/>promises to be amiable &amp; affectionate.</p>
               <p><lb/>I see I have generally begun my journal <lb/>with describing the bodily
                  progress she <lb/>has made, and I will keep to the <lb/>proper order of
                  things.</p>
               <pb n="35"/>
               <p><lb/>She can manage to walk by herself <lb/>with the a<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sistance of chairs, the sofa &amp;c <lb/>and the natural consequence of
                  this <unclear unit="word" quantity="1"></unclear><note resp="#mjk">This word, apparently 3-4 characters in length, has not been identified by previous editors. Clement Shorter in his 1923 edition, and Anita Wilson and J.A.V. Chapple in their 1996 edition, both silently delete this word, presumably because it does not appear to materially alter the meaning of the surrounding text <q>this exercise of the muscles of her legs</q>. It may have been a false start of the word <q>exercise</q>, which was later crossed out. There appears to be a squiggled strikethrough across the letters, a symbol Gaskell uses elsewhere in the journal when she wishes to make a change. </note>
                  <lb/>exercise of the muscles of her legs, is that <lb/>they have become more
                  developed &amp; conse=<lb/>=quently stronger; indeed her whole body <lb/>bespeaks
                  her a more healthy child. There <lb/>is that mottled look on the flesh, which
                  <lb/>gives such joy to a <!--flag this-->Mother's eye. She has <lb/>eight single,
                  and four double teeth, and <lb/>suffers <hi rend="underline">comparatively</hi>
                  little when she cuts <lb/>them. There is lo<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s of spirits &amp; appetite, <lb/>but no fits, or even fever, and spirits
                  &amp; <lb/>appetite come back, &amp; bring their atten=<lb/>=dant good-humour when
                  the cause <lb/>is removed. She has a colour like a <lb/>cherry, instead of the
                  shlushed wavering <lb/>red it used to be; and certainly with <lb/>health, beauty
                  has come; and I confe<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s <lb/>I think beauty a desirable thing. True <pb n="36"/><lb/>like most
                  other gifts, it has its tempta=<lb/>=tions, but still it is a high gift in the
                  <lb/>influence it irresistably gives its po<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>se<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sor <lb/>over others- an influence which may be <lb/>used for such noble
                  purposes.</p>
               <p><lb/>In general she is very sweet-tempered; <lb/>true there are little bursts of pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sion <lb/>which will require watchfulne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s &amp; care, <lb/>but she soon <unclear unit="character" quantity="1"
                     reason="squiggles"/><!-- This appears to be possibly an s, accidentally added and consequently crossed out. --> puts up her finger, and <lb/>says "hush" &amp; offers to ki<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s the person she <lb/>has offended against. Another more <lb/>difficult
                     <hi rend="underline">fault</hi>? is her disobedience- <lb/>She does not seem
                  at present to have <lb/>an idea of obedience; she is very obliging <lb/>and will
                  often do the thing we desire <lb/>her to do, but sometimes she resists very
                  <lb/>merrily &amp; in good-temper - puzzling <lb/>me sadly as to the right course
                  to take. <lb/>For instance when she comes near a <lb/>great gap between two chairs, I
                  call to <lb/>her to come back to <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Mama</persName>; she laughs<pb n="37"/><lb/>and still goes on; in gerenal I
                  get up <lb/>and take her up, &amp; let her down at her <lb/>starting point, where
                  she begins again, quite <lb/>good-tempered. Once or twice I have let <lb/>her go
                  on, &amp; she has had a slight tumble <lb/>which I have tried to tell her was in
                  <lb/>consequence of disobeying <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Mama</persName>- <lb/>She is very affectionate; when I am <lb/>poorly, or whenever
                  she thinks <sic>any one</sic>
                  <lb/>is hurt or sorry, she strokes their face, <lb/>saying "poor <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Mama</persName>, poor <persName
                     ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName> &amp;c"- <lb/>Her qreat delight just now is
                  in make-<lb/>believe letters; reading her own from <lb/><persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>, and introducing the names
                  <lb/>of all the things she knows, such as<lb/>"flowers, geese &amp;c. <choice>
                     <supplied resp="#mjk">"</supplied>
                  </choice> This and pictures <lb/>delight her extremely, but certainly <lb/>she is
                  not so independent as she should <lb/>be, and as I intended her to be. She
                  <lb/>has not much idea of amusing herself<pb n="38"/><lb/>which has been a great
                  error in her edu=<lb/>=cation hitherto, probably arising from her <lb/>delicacy in
                  part.<space type="long"/><!-- Likely a terminal paragraph break. -->
               She is remar=<lb/>=kably fond of children, and I am glad <lb/>to give her an <choice>
                     <reg>oppy</reg>
                     <supplied>opportunity</supplied>
                  </choice> of gratifying this <lb/>fondne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s by taking her this week to stay <lb/>a day or two at <persName
                     ref="#Mrs_Collins">Mrs. Collins</persName>, who has a <lb/>little girl five or
                  six months younger <lb/>than <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>. She seems to have <lb/>a good memory, and good natural
                  <lb/>talents; I hope they may never be neglected <lb/>through me.</p>
               <p><lb/>Lord thou knowest that the "sin that doth <lb/>so easily beset me" hath
                  overtaken me <lb/>once or twice even with this dear child- <lb/>but thou knowest
                  too how bitterly I have <lb/>repented, and how earnestly I mean to <lb/>try for
                  the future. Help thou my weak=<lb/>=ne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s, oh Lord, and ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s my endeavours to <lb/>conquer myself, and oh above all things <lb/>may
                  her presence be as holy to me, <lb/>checking each angry word that might <pb n="39"
                  /><lb/> injure the precious soul which thou hast <lb/>given to this little child. Ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s her, and ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s <lb/>her mother, who in sorrow confe<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>ses her fault <lb/>and prays for thy guidance in her future <lb/>conduct.
                  Oh Lord God Almighty ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s my <lb/>child, as thou seest fit &amp; best for her, <lb/>but may she
                  hear the glad words when <lb/>her mortal life is done, <quote>Well come good
                     <lb/>&amp; faithful servant, enter thou into the <lb/>joy of thy <persName
                        ref="#God">Lord</persName>.</quote>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="6">
               <head>Entry 6</head>
               <dateline>November 5, 1836</dateline>
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  26 months old; <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> was
                  expecting <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> at the time.</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Nine months have passed since the last entry.</head>
               <head>Length of Entry: Eleven and a half handwritten pages.</head>
               <p>The sixth entry foregrounds <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>’s belief that <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s behavior is heavily dependent upon and affected by her
                  physiological status. She follows her established pattern, beginning with a
                  description of <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s physical
                  development, followed by her intellectual and moral development. The entry’s
                  physical description surrounds <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s learning to walk, which she did at the late age of 22
                  months old. According to <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>, upon the advice of <persName ref="#Richard_Deane">Dr.
                     Richard Deane</persName>, a partner in her Uncle <persName ref="#Peter_Holland"
                     >Peter Holland</persName>’s medical practice in
                     <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName>, <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> was kept from being put on her feet during a summer visit
                  in 1836, when she would have been nearly 21 months old. Following a “violent
                  attack” which the Gaskells treated with a warm bath and a dose of castor oil,
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> cut her eye teeth, and
                  subsequently <quote>began almost suddenly to walk.</quote> The narrative of this
                  milestone step exemplifies <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>’s attitudes toward development throughout the diary: while
                  eager to see <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s
                  achievements, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>
                  insists on letting her daughters develop at their own pace, and concerns herself
                  primarily with helping <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> to
                  develop habits of perseverance and patience, rather than insisting on her gaining
                  any particular knowledge or skills.</p>
               <p>The remainder of the diary entry emphasizes <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s intellectual and moral development; she enjoys stories
                  and chatters often, but <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>, as with walking, intends to wait on formal instruction
                  until <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> is over 3 years old.
                  She is pleased with her daughter’s awareness of right and wrong, commenting that
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> often talks to herself
                  about being a <quote>dood dirl</quote> [good girl], and even recording a situation
                  in which she observed an adult engaged in something wrong and told her mother
                  about it. Although she shows evident pleasure in <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s growth, <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> again closes the entry
                  with anxious maternal worries. Recalling the unexpected death of an acquaintance’s
                  only child, she concludes with the observation of <quote>how very precious may the
                     remembrance of [events recorded in the journal] become,</quote> and a prayer
                  for her strength and resignation in the face of possible loss. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="6">
               <head>
                  <date when="1836-11-05">Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 5<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi>. 1836.</date>
               </head>
               <p><lb/>The greater part of this summer has been <lb/>pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sed in rather an unsettled way, what <lb/>with the visit to <placeName
                     ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName>, <placeName ref="#Warrington"
                     >Warrington</placeName>, and to <lb/>the sea-side, and I fear this is the only
                  ex=<lb/>=cuse I have for so long neglecting to enter <lb/>any-thing in my journal.
                  A great progre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s <lb/>has naturally been made by the dear little <lb/>subject since
                  writing last. I do not think <pb n="40"/><lb/>her health has had any material
                  draw-back. <lb/>though for some time her languor in attempt=<lb/>=ing to walk
                  caused me some uneasine<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s. <lb/>When we were at <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName>
                  (in <date>May</date>) <persName ref="#Richard_Deane">W<hi rend="superscript"
                        >m</hi>. <lb/>Deane</persName> quite forbid her being put upon her <lb/>feet
                  and the consequence of course was that <lb/>she lost the little idea of walking
                  which she <lb/>had before. At <placeName ref="#Prospect Hill">Prospect
                     Hill</placeName>she gained strength <lb/>though she had one violent attack,
                  (beginning <lb/>with violent screaming as if in pain), but <lb/> we put her
                  directly into warm water, &amp; <lb/>gave her castor oil, sending at the same
                  <lb/>time for a medical man, who decided <lb/>that the inflammatory state of her
                  body <lb/>was owing to being on the point of <lb/>cutting her eye-teeth. He said
                  the course <lb/>I had pursued before he came was decided=<lb/>=ly the best and
                  safest in all sudden attacks <lb/>with children. After these said eye-teeeth
                  <lb/>came through, as to speak <hi rend="underline">very</hi> exactly <lb/>in the
                  beginning of <date>July 1836</date>, when she was <pb n="41"/><lb/> two and twenty
                  months old, she began <lb/>almost suddenly to walk by herself, and <lb/>since then
                  her bodily strength has come on <lb/>very much indeed. For some time, indeed
                  <lb/>even now we are very careful to comply with <lb/>her request to be taken "up,
                  up", when she is <lb/>tired of walking, as I think the exercise <lb/>gives her
                  such a pleasurable feeling, that it <lb/>must be fatigue and not caprice that lead
                  <lb/>her to ask to be carried. She is very careful <lb/>and has a good idea of
                  danger; not like <lb/>some children who have been forced rather <lb/>too early to
                  their feet and seem not to be able <lb/>to measure distances. So much for her
                  <lb/>feats in the walking line. She has now <lb/>16 teeth, and we thinkn she is
                  cutting her <lb/>back double teeth, but as these give compa=<lb/>ratively little
                  pain I do not feel anxious <lb/>about them. I have often intended to
                  mea=<lb/>=sure her height, but somehow or other it has <pb n="42"/><lb/>hitherto
                  slipped through; but from her frocks &amp; <lb/><!-- check this word-->que<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s she has grown a good deal these last <lb/>eight weeks, and good need
                  she had of it, for <lb/>she was a little rolly-polly before.</p>
               <p>She is a famous chatter-box seldom letting <lb/>her little tongue rest either with
                  sense <!--is this an f written over into an r?-->or non=<lb/>=sense, and it is
                  amusing to hear her talk <lb/>in this latter fashion, inventing so many new
                  <lb/>sounds in such varied tones. Her great de=<lb/>=light is in hearing "tories,"
                  and little scraps <lb/>of verse; and I think she shows a pretty <lb/>good memory
                  in repeating them again. <lb/>We have not begun yet to teach her any thing
                  <lb/>feeling in no hurry to urge her little capacity <lb/>forward, and in this we
                  have been in many <lb/>ways confirmed. We heard the opinion of <lb/>a medical man
                  lately, who said that till <lb/>the age of three years or there abouts, the brain
                  <lb/>of an infant appeared constantly to be verging <lb/>on inflammation, which
                  any <metamark rend="carat"/><add place="above"><hi rend="underline"
                     >little</hi></add> exce<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s of excite=<lb/>=ment might produce. If we give her habits <lb/>of
                  observation, attention &amp; perseverance, in <pb n="43"/><lb/>whatever objects
                  her little mind may be occu=<lb/>=pied with, I shall think we are laying a
                  <lb/>good foundation, and four years old will be <lb/>time enough to begin with
                     <hi rend="underline">le<choice>
                        <sic>&#383;</sic>
                        <reg>s</reg>
                     </choice>sons</hi> &amp;c, &amp; even <lb/>then it shall be in compliance with
                  her new <lb/>wish to learn, which wish I must try to excite. <lb/>So much for <hi
                     rend="underline">intellect</hi>. Now for morals.</p>
               <p><lb/>There have been times when I have felt, oh! <lb/>so cast down by her
                  wrong-doing, and as I <lb/>think I am very easily impre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sible, I have<lb/> fancied there must have been some great <lb/>mismanagement
                  to produce such little obsti=<lb/>nate fits, and whole hours of wilfulne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s. </p>
               <p><lb/>I do not however think that this has been <lb/>often the case, and when it
                  has, my cooler <lb/>judgement has been aware of some little <lb/>circumstance
                  connected with her physical <lb/>state that has in some measure accounted <lb/>for
                  it. For instance, she, (like her mother) re=<lb/>=quires a great deal of sleep.
                  She is <hi rend="underline">always</hi><pb n="44"/>
                  <lb/>in bed, and asleep by seven, frequently earlier, <lb/>and seldom awakens
                  before six at the earliest. <lb/>Then she requires from two to three hours sleep
                  <lb/>in the middle of the day, and if by any chance <lb/>her time for sleep goes
                  by she is weary, fretful <lb/>and as unlike the merry happy little creature
                  <lb/>she is in general as po<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sible.<!--unsure if this is true paragraph break; long gap mid line--><space type="long"/>
               We have <lb/>been puzzled for a punishment. The usual <lb/>one, putting the
                  little offender into a corner <lb/>had no effect with her, as she made it into
                  <lb/>a game to "<hi rend="underline">d</hi><add place="above">g</add>o into a
                  corner and be naughty <lb/>little girl;" so the last we have tried is <lb/>putting
                  her into a high chair, from which <lb/>she cannot get out, and leaving her there
                  <lb/>(always in the same room with one of us) <lb/>till some little sign of sorrow
                  is shown. <lb/>This with grave and sorrowful looks on our <lb/>part has generally
                  had the desired effect <lb/>She often talks to herself about the consequences
                  <lb/>of her conduct. "Baby <hi rend="underline">d</hi>ood <hi rend="underline"
                     >d</hi>irl, make <lb/><persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName> and <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Mama</persName> happy." "Baby not dood<pb
                     n="45"/>
                  <lb/>dirl, <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Mama</persName> so sorry." &amp;c I think
                  for <lb/>so young a child she has a pretty correct idea <lb/>as to whether actions
                  are right or wrong. I've <lb/>had an instance lately when <hi rend="underline"
                     >some</hi>
                  <hi rend="underline">one</hi>, in <lb/>anger did what was decidedly wrong in her
                  <lb/>presence, without considering how holy that <lb/>little creature made the
                  place. She took no <lb/>notice, at the time but the next morning <lb/>told me of
                  it, adding <q>that <hi rend="underline">was</hi> naughty.</q> Though <lb/>much
                  interested in preserving her love and <lb/>re<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>pect for the person to whom I allude, I <lb/>knew it was my duty not to
                  weaken her <lb/>power of discriminating, &amp; said <q>it was very <lb/>naughty, but
                  she was very sorry now &amp;c.</q> <lb/>A few weeks ago she got a habit of refusing
                  <lb/>her food, saying <q>bye-bye</q> &amp;c when a spoon=<lb/>=ful was offered to her
                  which she did not <lb/>quite approve. I found the best plan was <lb/>to take her
                  at her word, and quietly sent <lb/>the plate away, which at first produed <pb
                     n="46"/><lb/>sad fits of crying, and throwing herself back, but <lb/>after once
                  or twice she became le<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s saucy, and <lb/>takes her food very pleasantly now. I think <lb/>she is
                  not a greedy child, whatever her other <lb/>faults may be. She knows when she has
                  had <lb/>enough. She gave me a very pretty little instance<lb/> of unselfishne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s when we were last at <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName>
                  <lb/>which pleased me very much. We were calling <lb/>at <persName
                     ref="#MaryAnn_Deane">Mr<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Deane</persName>s who has
                  two children, one about <lb/>9 months older, the other about that much
                  <lb/>younger than <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>. A few
                  comfits <lb/> were thrown on the carpet, which the youngest <lb/>child (little
                     <persName ref="#Emily_Deane">Emily</persName>) could hardly manage to <lb/>pick
                  up. My own dear <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> however
                  <lb/>did not put one into her own mouth, though <lb/>as fond of them as could be,
                  but crammed <lb/>them into little <persName ref="#Emily_Deane">Emily</persName>.
                  It made my heart <lb/> glad.</p>
               <p><lb/>I am not aware that any promise <lb/>has been made to her that has not been
                  <lb/>strictly fulfilled. And the consequence is <pb n="47"/><lb/>she has a firm
                  reliance on our word, and a <lb/>pretty good idea of giving up a present
                  <lb/>pleasure to secure a future one, feeling <lb/>sure that the promise will be
                  performed. <lb/>While at <placeName ref="#Grange">Grange</placeName> it was nece<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sary for her to <lb/>bathe, and I dreaded it for her. Luckily <lb/> her
                     <persName ref="#Anne_Gaskell">Aunt Ann</persName>, a capital bather was with
                  <lb/>us, and undertook the charge of her, which <lb/>was so much better than being
                  frightened <lb/>by being given over to a strange woman in <lb/>an uncouth dre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s. We made the period of <lb/>suspense as short as po<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sible, undre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sing her <lb/>directly, and giving her her plunges imme=<lb/>=diately. I
                  stood on the rocks with a shawl <lb/>ready to receive her &amp; give her a
                  biscuit, &amp; <lb/>though she often said while being undre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sed <lb/>"Baby not bathe Mama," we never had any <lb/>crying or
                  screaming. <!--long break within line again here.--> She has lately <lb/>had
                  occasion to take one or two doses<!--smudge in this word, look more closely-->of
                  Epsom <pb n="48"/><lb/>salts, and I have always told her before hand <lb/>they
                  were bad bad, but were to do her good, &amp; <lb/>she has taken them directly,
                  looking however <lb/>thoroughly<!--letters missing, or wrong word here?-->
                  inclined to cry when the cup is taken <lb/>from her lips, but a biscuit as a
                  reward <lb/>soon puts a stop to this. <space type="long"/><!--long gap-->Sometimes as a <lb/>proof of
                  our pleasure we have given her <lb/>a spunge biscuit, 1/2 a doz comfits, or a bit
                  of <lb/>pomfret cake, but we try not to make her ex=<lb/>-pect these things, which
                  are only occasional <lb/>but to depend for her reward on our pleased
                  <lb/>countenances and expre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sions, and our <lb/>willingne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s to play and romp with her. <lb/>This love of an earthly parent's
                  approbation <lb/>we hope in time to lead into a higher feeling.</p>
               <p><lb/>A few weeks since she saw the <lb/>funeral of a young girl in her walk with
                     <lb/><persName ref="#Betsy_household">Betsy</persName>, and showing in her way
                  some <lb/>curiosity on the subject, <persName ref="#Betsy_household"
                     >Betsy</persName> injudiciously <lb/>but very naturally told her it was a poor
                  <lb/>girl that they were going to put into a hole <pb n="48"/><lb/>and cover her
                  up with earth. This made a <lb/>great impre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sion on her. Once or twice when <lb/>she has been awakened in the night,
                  she <lb/>has so directly referred <!--word unclear!-->to it with signs of
                  <lb/>affright, that we have concluded she has <lb/>been dreaming of it, and we
                  have done our <lb/>best to counteract the feelings excited by <lb/>telling her the
                  girl was very happy, and was <lb/>gone to <hi rend="underline">bo</hi>-<hi
                     rend="underline">bo</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p><lb/>She is very touching in her sweet little <lb/>marks of affection. Once or twice
                  when I <lb/>have seemed unhappy about little things <lb/> she has come and held up
                  her sweet mouth <lb/>to be ki<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sed. Last night I was in pain, &amp; <lb/>made a sort of moan. She was
                  lying by <lb/>me apparently asleep, but as if her gentle <lb/>instinct of love
                  prompted her even then, <lb/>she peeped to me, saying "Ki<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s, Mama." <lb/>These are trifles but how very precious <lb/>may the
                  remembrance of them become.</p>
               <pb n="49"/>
               <p><lb/>We yesterday heard of a connection of <lb/><persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell"
                     >William</persName>'s who had just lost his only child <lb/>a fine lad of nine
                  or ten, by a sudden at=<lb/>=tack of croup. His father and mother were
                  <lb/>wrapped in the boy, who had every promise of <lb/>excellence. Oh! how I
                  trembled when I heard of <lb/>it, and felt how insecure these "treasures in
                  <lb/>earthen ve<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sels" are.</p>
               <p>
                  <lb/>Oh God! give me that spirit which can feel <lb/>and say not my will but thine
                  be done. <lb/>Teach me to love this darling chlld with perfect <lb/>submi<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sion to thy decrees. I dare hardly think <lb/>of the uncertain future,
                  but thou wilt uphold <lb/>me in time of trial, and into thy hands <lb/>I commit my
                  treasure. So with her Oh Lord <lb/>as seemeth best unto thee, for thou art a God
                  <lb/>of Love &amp; will not causele<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sly afflict. Ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s her <lb/>in every way I earnestly beseech thee, through <lb/>Jesus
                  Christ our Lord.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="7">
               <head>Entry 7</head>
               <dateline>December 9, 1837</dateline>
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  3 years, 3 months; <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, aged 10
                  months</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Thirteen months since the previous entry.</head>
               <head>Length of Entry: Twelve handwritten pages</head>
               <p>The seventh entry spans twelve handwritten manuscript pages, one of the longest
                  entries in the diary. In this entry <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> introduces two new individuals; her second daughter,
                     <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Margaret Emily</persName>, called
                     <quote>Meta</quote>, and her maternal aunt, <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s adoptive
                     <quote>more-than-mother</quote>
                  <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Hannah Lumb</persName>. <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> was a *widowed woman who raised
                     <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> after her
                     <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Holland_Stevenson">mother</persName>’s death when she
                  was only thirteen months old. Shortly following the birth of <persName
                     ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt
                     Lumb</persName> suffered a stroke that marked the beginning of her final
                  illness. <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> had been staying
                  with her at the time, during her <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >mother</persName>’s confinement, and both <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> and one-month-old
                     <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> traveled to be with <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> and <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> early in March until her death
                  in May. These events, <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>’s birth and
                     <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>’s death, are alluded
                  to by <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> early in the
                  entry, when she writes that “sad excuses” in some part account for the year-long
                  lapse between this diary entry and the one that preceded it. </p>
               <p>Much of the entry is told looking back on the months that have passed between the
                  entries, during which time <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> was born,
                  and <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> passed away. The
                  events were closely connected, in fact; <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> had gone to stay with <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb"
                     >Aunt Lumb</persName> had a paralytic stroke, and <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> traveled to
                     <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName>, with newborn <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell"
                     >Meta</persName> and a servant, Betsy, and remained there in rented rooms with
                  both girls for nearly two months until <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt
                     Lumb</persName>’s death on May 1st. A letter, dated <date when="1837-03-18">18
                     March 1837</date>, recounts <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>’s experience of <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt
                     Lumb</persName>’s illness. There is also a second letter, written to <persName
                     ref="#Holbrook_Gaskell">Holbrook Gaskell</persName>, tentatively dated in 1837
                  as <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> is the only child
                  mentioned; part of the letter is missing. The letter details plans for the
                  possibility of negotiating a new servant.</p>
               <p>The diary entry looks back on these events and comments tenderly on <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>’s care of both <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> and <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>, and recounts <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s careful management of
                  the situation with <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, who
                  was not told that <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> had
                  died. The later part of the entry discusses the differences between the two
                  sisters, commenting that <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, already
                  ten months old, is livelier and physically developing earlier than <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, crawling “famously”. <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, to <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s pleasure, has a very
                  “acute” conscience, and is becoming “useful and independent,” often willing to
                  share with her sister and generally obedient and cheerful. <persName
                     ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, however, is <quote>saucy</quote>,
                     <quote>clever</quote>, and <quote>not so gentle</quote> as her elder
                  sister.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="7">
               <!-- verification complete 1/1/20 & 1/5/20-->
               <head>
                  <date when="1837-12-09">Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 9<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi>. 18<hi rend="underline">37</hi></date>
               </head>
               <p><lb/>I feel quite ashamed to see that more than <lb/>a year has pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sed since I last wrote. There have <lb/>been some sad excuses to be sure.
                  I had very <lb/>bad health till my dear little <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell"
                     >Meta</persName> was born, <lb/><date when="1837-02-05">February 5<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1837</date>, and I had hardly recovered <lb/>my
                  strength when (<date when="1837-03-10">March 10<hi rend="superscript"
                     >th</hi>.</date>) I received a sum=<lb break="no"/>=mons to <placeName
                     ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName>. My dearest <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>, my <lb/>more than mother had
                  had a paralytic stroke <lb/>on <date when="1837-03-08">Wednesday March 8<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>; For eight weeks I re=<lb break="no"
                  />=mained in lodgings at <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName>, with
                  my two <lb/>little girls, and our dear servant <persName ref="#Betsy_household"
                     >Betsy</persName>; and on <lb/><date when="1837-05-01">May 1<hi
                        rend="superscript">st</hi>.</date> I lost my best friend. May <persName
                     ref="#God">God</persName> reward <lb/>her for all her kindne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s to me.</p>
               <p><lb/>After that I was much out of health for some time <lb/>and went to <placeName
                     ref="#Crosby">Crosby</placeName> in <date when="1837-07">July</date>. In <date
                     when="1837-09">September</date>
                  <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">William</persName>
                  <pb n="50"/><lb/>and I went into <placeName ref="#Wales">Wales</placeName> for
                  three weeks, leaving <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Mari=<lb break="no"
                     />anne</persName> with <persName ref="#Bessey_Holland">Bessy
                  Holland</persName>, and <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> with
                     <persName ref="#MaryAnn_Deane">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>.
                     <lb/>Deane</persName>. We have lost our servant <persName
                     ref="#Betsy_household">Betsy</persName>, who was <lb/>obliged to leave us,
                  being wanted at home, in conse=<lb break="no"/>=quence of the death of a sister.
                  But we still <lb/>keep her as a friend, and she has been to stay <lb/>with us
                  several weeks this autumn. Her place <lb/>is supplied by <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Barlow_household">Elizabeth</persName>, a clever servant, and
                  who <lb/>is very kind to the children especially to little <lb/><persName
                     ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>. <space type="long"/>I have given this
                  little account of the <lb/>changes in our domestic relations, that if this
                  <lb/>book be given to <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, (as
                  I hope it will be) <lb/>after my death she may understand more fully <lb/>any
                  thing I may have occasion to allude to. <lb/>When my most dearly loved <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt</persName> left this house <lb/>for the last
                  time, (<date when="1837-01-15">Jan<hi rend="superscript">ry</hi> 15<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1837.</date>) she took <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>
                  <lb/>back with her to <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName>; to stay
                  with her over <lb/>the time of my approaching confinement. As <lb/><persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>'s eyesight had failed her very
                  much, <pb n="51"/>
                  <lb/>she was unable to write; so I had no particular ac=<lb break="no"/>counts of
                  my darling; only general news of her health.</p>
               <p>
                  <lb/>But since, I have asked my cousins &amp;c to tell me <lb/>all the particulars
                  of the seven weeks that <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">M.A</persName>
                  <choice>
                     <sic>staid</sic>
                     <reg>stayed</reg>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>with <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> before she was
                  seized with her last <lb/>illne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s. <space type="short"/>They say, that <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> seemed so very <lb/>fond of
                     <q>her little <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName></q>. One
                  day some one met <lb/>my <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt</persName> out
                  of doors; she had been about an hour <lb/>out, and said she was hastening home,
                  for she did <lb/>not think she had left <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">M.
                     A.</persName> so long before; The little <lb/>girl slept in a cot by <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>'s bed; <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>
                  <lb/>gave her, her breakfast, sitting on her knee, by a win=<lb break="no"/>=dow,
                  with many loving little jokes between them. <lb/><persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> walked out with her, when the
                     wea=<lb break="no"/>ther permitted. And it was to <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>, that <lb/><persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> ran when in any little distre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s; and to <lb/>her that she always clung.</p>
               <p><lb/>The very day <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> was
                  seized with her fatal <pb n="52"/>
                  <lb/>attack, she had been with <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> in <persName ref="#MaryAnn_Deane">M<hi rend="underline"
                        >rs</hi>
                     <lb/>Deane</persName>'s <choice>
                     <sic>poney</sic>
                     <reg>pony</reg>
                  </choice>-carriage to the <placeName ref="#Infant school">Infant
                     school</placeName>, and <lb/>was so pleased with <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>'s pleasure.</p>
               <p><lb/>That evening about 1/2 past 10, she had a para=<lb break="no"/>=lytic stroke.
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">M.A.</persName> was as usual in her little
                  sofa <lb/>bed by <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>'s, and
                  remained there till <lb/>morning, when she wanted according to her custom <lb/>to
                  come into <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>'s bed. But
                     <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>
                  <lb/>did not heed the little voice that kept petitioning <lb/>to be taken in, and
                  when they told her <q><persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt <lb/>Lumb</persName>
                     was poorly.</q> she kept saying <q><persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt
                        Lumb</persName>
                     <lb/>tell me if you are poorly.</q> Of course she was <lb/>sent to a friend's <choice>
                     <sic>till</sic>
                     <reg>until</reg>
                  </choice> I came.</p>
               <p><lb/>We were confined to two little bed-rooms in that <lb/>unhappy eight weeks,
                  and the little girls could <lb/>hardly ever go out. But <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> was a good <lb/>little comfort,
                  though in such trying circumstances <lb/>to a child's temper. <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> asked to see <lb/>her, about a
                  week after her first seizure; and <lb/>I took <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >MA</persName> in. But the room was darkened <pb n="53"/><lb/>gloomy; <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> had had leeches to her head
                  <lb/>and it was bound up, almost corpse-like, with <lb/>a handkerchief. <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> was frightened I <lb/>think; and
                  I was afraid <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName>, though not
                  <lb/>herself, and blind, (alas!) perceived it. The next time <lb/>she begged to
                  have a night-cap put on, and had <lb/>a fig put behind her pillow, and <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">M.A.</persName> was recon=<lb break="no"/>ciled, and
                  played about the room. She went in seve=<lb break="no"/>=ral times, and her coming
                  always gave <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt <lb/>Lumb</persName>
                  pleasure. It was such a beautiful spring <lb/>morning, that <date
                     when="1837-05-01">1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of May</date>, when <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> died; <lb/> such a contrast to
                  the dreary weather before.</p>
               <p><lb/>On the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> we all came back to <placeName
                     ref="#Manchester">Manchester</placeName>; and <lb/>then I rather began to fear
                  that the long confine=<lb break="no"/>ment in small rooms had <hi rend="underline"
                     >told</hi> upon <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>'s
                  <lb/>temper, poor darling! She was fretful, and rather <lb/>obstinate sometimes.
                  But <persName ref="#Betsy_household">Betsy</persName> was leaving us <pb n="54"
                  /><lb/>and a new servant coming, which I do think is <lb/>a trial for a child. It
                  soon wore off with patient; and <lb/>gentle treatment from her <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Gaskell_Holland">Aunt Eliza</persName>, who was <lb/>here at
                  the time, comforting and being of use. <lb/>We have never told her that <persName
                     ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt Lumb</persName> was dead, <lb/>fearing that a
                  child's material ideas, might connect <lb/>gloom with the idea of one so ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sed. <quote>Gone to the <lb/>rest prepared for the People of God!</quote>
                  But I often talk <lb/>of her, and try to keep alive the recollection of her
                  <lb/>love and tenderne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s, and show her <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt
                  Lumb</persName>'s <lb/>picture, that even her bodily appearance (a fit shrine
                  <lb/>for so chastened and pure a spirit) may stand <lb/>forth clear and distinct
                  among her childish remem=<lb break="no"/>=brances. One day we were talking, and
                  she said <q><persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt <lb/>Lumb</persName> was
                     poorly;</q>
                  <q>No,</q> I said, <q>she is well and happy <lb/>now.</q> Is she, replied my dear
                  little girl, <q>Oh then <lb/>I am so glad; let me go and coax her.</q> And
                  <lb/>since she has been at <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName> (in <date when="1837-09">September</date>)<pb n="55"/><lb/>she has told me <persName ref="#Hannah_Holland_Lumb">Aunt
                     Lumb</persName> did not live with <lb/><persName ref="#Abigail_Holland">Aunt
                     Ab</persName> now; she had left that house. I longed to <lb/>say she was
                     <quote>gone to a house not made with hands, <lb/>eternal, in the
                     heavens.</quote> But I thought I had better <lb/>not, for to her it would have
                  been unintelligible at <lb/>present.
                  <!--pen shift--><!-- Ink change; darker strokes follow -->Before she went to
                     <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName> in <date when="1837-09"
                     >September</date>, <lb/>she had again a few days of untractablene<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s, and obsti=<lb break="no"/>=nacy. But I think she was very judiciously
                  managed <lb/>while there, for she came back a good little darling, so <lb/>gentle
                  and loving. Indeed I should say that her <lb/>temper was very sweet, and her
                  disposition very <lb/>affectionate. Her little conscience too is becoming
                  <lb/>very acute and well-judging. I think most of her <lb/>faults are of
                  inadvertence (hardly <hi rend="underline">faults</hi>;) ex=<lb break="no"/>=cept
                  now and then when she has a fit of obsti=<lb break="no"/>=nacy; but we are very
                  steady in fulfilling our <hi rend="underline">threat</hi><pb n="56"/><lb/>of
                  punishment, so these little obstinacies are gradually <lb/>disappearing. Our
                  punishment for her is taking her <lb/>and leaving her alone for five minutes or
                  so, in a <lb/>light room. We tell her the length of time that she <lb/>may not
                  think we are influenced by caprice, or <lb/>that she gains her point (of leaving
                  the room) by <lb/>crying. Once and once only have we had recourse <lb/>to a
                  severer punishment. It was one Sunday <choice>
                     <sic>eveng</sic>
                     <reg>evening</reg>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>it may be about five weeks ago; we were trying to <lb/>teach her, her
                  letters, more by way of occupation for <lb/>her these long winter evenings, than
                  from any anxie=<lb break="no"/>=ty as to her progre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s in learning. She knew all the <lb/>vowels but refused to say A. All the
                  others she would <lb/>say, but would not even
                  <!-- Unsure of word, very illegible --> repeat A after us. We <lb/>got the slate,
                  and drew it for her; but she persevered. <lb/><persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell"
                     >Meta</persName> was asleep so we were unwilling to provoke <lb/>the violent
                  crying, which generally ensues when <lb/>she is taken upstairs; so <persName
                     ref="#Wm_Gaskell">W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>.</persName> gave her a slap
                     <pb n="57"/><lb/>on her hand <!-- Verification paused, 1/1/20 --> every time
                  she refused to say it, till <lb/>at last she said it quite pat. Still I am sure we
                  <lb/>were so unhappy that we cried, when she was gone <lb/>to bed. And I don't
                  know if it was right. If not <lb/>pray, dear <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>, forgive us.</p>
               <p><lb/>Since then we have not attempted any more le<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sons <lb/>till she shows some desire to resume them; and I <lb/>think she
                  is coming round, for she delights in <lb/>getting a book, and saying to herself,
                     <q>This is A</q>
                  <lb/>or O, as the case may be &amp;c.</p>
               <p><lb/>She is not by any means forward for her age; <lb/>but not at all deficient in
                  any thing. She has <lb/>never asked any question whatever that would <lb/>lead to
                  any, even the most simple truths, of <lb/>religion. I am on the watch for any
                  thing of <lb/>the sort.</p>
               <p><lb/>She is getting both useful, and independent. She <pb n="58"/><lb/>does little
                  things for herself and other people, and <lb/>thinks of things herself, such as
                  fetching her <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName>'s <lb/>slippers &amp;c.
                  Today he was going out; and she had <lb/>gone on a me<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sage into the kitchen, but when <lb/>she heard him trying to open the
                  front door, she <lb/>ran, calling out Stop Papa Papa., you must <lb/>give me a ki<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s before you go.</p>
               <p><lb/>And now for my little <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>; 10
                  months old <lb/>on the fifth of this month. She has a much <lb/>more pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sionate temper than <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>; per=<lb break="no"/>=haps much livelier. But I sometimes
                  fancy that <lb/>8 weeks spent day and night in one little <lb/>close room, may
                  have had some influence on <lb/>her temper. She is very bright and sunny when
                  <lb/>all goes right, and very affectionate; particu=<lb break="no"/>=larly to her
                     <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName> and <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Barlow_household">Elizabeth</persName>, little, saucy <lb/>girl
                  she prefers them both to her Mama. <lb/>I fancy she will be more clever than her
                  <lb/>elder sister, if not so gentle. And there are <pb n="59"/><lb/>very fine
                  materials to work upon I am con=<lb break="no"/>=vinced, if I but knew how. I am
                  sometimes a=<lb break="no"/>fraid <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Barlow_household"
                     >Elizabeth</persName> spoils her. She has had very good <lb/>health with the
                  exception of one week, when <lb/>she was about 9 months and a fortnight old;
                  <lb/>the same age and cutting the same teeth as <lb/><persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">MA</persName> was when she had her terrible illne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s. <lb/>But if this was anything of the sort, it was <lb/>not nearly so
                  violent.</p>
               <p><lb/>She has now had four teeth for 2 months or <lb/>more. She is taller and
                  slighter than <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">M. A.</persName>
                  <lb/>and stronger, as she can roll and crawl <lb/>away famously on the carpet. She
                  is <lb/>like <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">M. A.</persName>; not quite such
                  a pretty com=<lb break="no"/>=plexion, and no dimples, but longer eye=<lb
                     break="no"/>=lashes. She <choice>
                     <reg>cannot</reg>
                     <sic>can not</sic>
                  </choice> quite stand by taking hold of <pb n="60"/><lb/>any thing, but very
                  nearly. She has no little accom=<lb break="no"/>=plishments yet, but that is only
                  for want of being <lb/>taught. She knows us all by name. Once or twice <lb/>I have
                  heard <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Barlow_household">Elizabeth</persName> distracting
                  her attention <lb/>when in a little pet<!--or fit? "pet" Acc. to Wilson; --> by
                  telling her to look for <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName>
                  <lb/>or Dicky (the bird) when they were not there. This <lb/>I am afraid I did not
                  sufficiently check.</p>
               <p><lb/>The two dear little sisters are very fond of one <lb/>another. <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> gives up any thing she has
                  <lb/>if <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> wants it. Almost too much I
                  fancy <lb/>sometimes. And <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> looks so
                  relyingly for <lb/><persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>'s help
                  if she has lost any little play=<lb break="no"/>=thing or in any distre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s. And she crows and dances <lb/>when she hears <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>'s voice. Oh! how I <lb/>hope this
                  love will last. I must do my best to <lb/>cherish it. Oh <persName ref="#God"
                     >God</persName> help me in all my good <lb/>resolutions with regard to these
                  two dear children, <lb/>for without thee I have no strength. Amen</p>
               <pb n="61"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="8">
               <head>Entry 8</head>
               <dateline>March 25, 1838</dateline>
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  3 and a half; <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, aged 13 months</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Three and a half months since the previous entry.</head>
               <head>Length of Entry: Five and a half handwritten pages.</head>
               <p>In the dateline of this entry, the year is obscured, so that an 8 is superimposed
                  over the seven. As the entry follows an entry for <date when="1837-12">December
                     1837</date>, however, and the entirety of the diary continues in chronological
                  sequence, it is clear that this entry was written in <date when="1838-03-25"
                     >1838</date>. Although <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> is at this
                  time over a year old, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> appears rushed in this entry and writes only about
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, who is to begin
                  <q>Infant School</q>. <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s
                  maternal responsibility surrounding the education of her daughters is a fitting
                  topic in the wake of <persName ref="#Queen_Victoria">Queen Victoria</persName>’s
                  accession to the throne nine months earlier, in <date when="1837-06">June
                     1837</date>. The coronation had not yet taken place, but the country must have
                  been watching closely as they prepared for rule under a female monarch. The entry
                  foregrounds <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s
                  indecisiveness or doubt in maternal choices, and she uses the journal to weigh
                  both sides of the decision. On one hand, she worries, <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> may learn things at school from
                  the other children that she would not wish her to know, and may care less for her
                  home, but on the other hand, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> reasons, school will give her the opportunity to learn
                  obedience and perseverance, which are characteristics that <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> and her <persName
                     ref="#Wm_Gaskell">husband</persName> are firmly devoted to. They are not
                  concerned with <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s learning
                  much in the school, so much as her developing the necessary habits that will
                  underly her learning later. </p>
               <p>The entry builds upon <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>’s concerns with <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s education by discussing her initial mother-daughter
                  conversations regarding religious belief. <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> has attended her first Chapel service, on Christmas Day in
                     <date when="1837">1837</date>, at age 3, and <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> is pleased with her
                  understanding of the teachings so far. <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s language is developing; she knows her letters and can
                  spell a few words, and recite a poem. </p>
               <p>The entry’s closing allows an intriguing glimpse into the connections <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> makes between this early
                  diary and her later writing career. In the final paragraph, where she bemoans the
                  lack of time to write anything about <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell"
                  >Meta</persName>, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>
                  writes pointedly, <quote>I must devote my next ‘chapter’ to her.</quote> This is
                  the first moment in the diary in which she likens her writing to its commercial
                  counterpart. This connection notably follows <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s first publication. The
                  previous year, in <date when="1837-01">January 1837</date>, only a month before
                     <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>’s birth, <quote>Sketches Among
                     The Poor,</quote> a poem co-written by the Gaskells, had appeared in
                     <bibl>Blackwoods</bibl>’. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="8">
               <!-- Verification Complete 12/29/19 -->
               <head>
                  <date when="1838-03-25">March 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1838. Sunday
                        <time>Evening</time>.</date>
               </head>
               <p><lb/>There is a new era in the little life of my dear <lb/>little girl. Tomorrow
                  she goes to an <placeName ref="#Infant school">Infant School</placeName>. <lb/>I think I am naturally
                  undecided, or rather <lb/>perhaps apt to repent my decision when it is <lb/>too
                  late, but now I am beginning to wonder if <lb/>I have done right about this
                  darling. There is <lb/>much to be said on each side. It <hi rend="underline"
                     >may</hi> weaken <lb/>her pleasure in home, her love for us all, her
                  <lb/>confidence in me, at present such a ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sing <lb/>to me; - she <hi rend="underline">may</hi> meet with children
                  who may <lb/>teach her the meaning of things of which at <lb/>present we desire to
                  keep her ignorant, that <lb/>we may give her correct ideas when her <unclear
                     unit="word" quantity="1">mind</unclear>
                  <lb/>is more advanced; such as Death, falsehood <lb/>&amp;c &amp;c. But our
                  reasons for wishing her to go <lb/>to school, are also strong; not to advance her
                     <pb n="62"/><lb/>rapidly in any branch of learning, for <persName
                     ref="#Wm_Gaskell">William</persName>
                  <lb/>and I agree in not caring for this; but to per=<lb break="no"/>=fect her
                  habits of obedience, to give her an idea <lb/>of conquering difficulties by
                  perseverance; and <lb/>to make her apply steadily for a short time. <lb/>She is to
                  go at half past nine, and come <lb/>home at 12; and certainly not in the after=<lb
                     break="no"/>-noon at present, if ever. I think enough of <lb/>application may
                  be got in the morning, and <lb/>I shall like her to be with me, with <persName
                     ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, <lb/>out of doors &amp;c &amp;c, in the
                  afternoon. I am <lb/>sometimes afraid of becoming a lazy <lb/>mother, willing to
                  send my children <lb/>away from me, and forgetting that on <hi rend="underline"
                     >me</hi>
                  <lb/>lies the heaviest responsibility. I will try and <lb/>be better in this
                  respect. I intend as much <lb/>as I can, to fetch her from school myself; <lb/>I
                  have several reasons for wishing to do this. <!-- check punctuation? Wilson and Shattock have period -->
                  <lb/>One is that she may not be much out of school <pb n="63"/><lb/>with the other
                  children, though I have reason <lb/>to believe them to be all respectable, and
                  well <lb/>brought up; but as she will be younger, she may <lb/>the more easily
                  catch up any false ideas. <lb/>Then I mean to lead her to tell me in the
                  <lb/>course of her walk home, all the little events <lb/>that have occurred in
                  school. I can perhaps <lb/>set her right if her ideas get confused, and I <lb/>can
                  sympathize with and advise her. <lb/>I have tried to decide in this matter for the
                  <lb/>best, and now we must await the result; only <lb/>pray for <persName
                     ref="#God">God</persName>'s ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sing upon her.</p>
               <p>Since I last wrote, she and I have begun to <lb/>talk together about religion. I
                  have told <lb/>her the simple truths I thought she could <lb/>understand, such as
                     <persName ref="#God">God</persName>'s goodne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s and love, <lb/>His watching over us in the silent hours of <lb/>the
                  night &amp;c. I think she has now right ideas <pb n="64"/><lb/>as far as they go,
                  about this important subject. <lb/>At first she perplexed me very much by her
                  <lb/>very <hi rend="underline">material</hi> questions. <q>When does
                     <!-- encode the emdash? --> - go to <lb/>bed,</q> &amp;c. But now we talk
                  together in a low <lb/>tone, and she likes to hear about him, and refers <lb/>very
                  properly to him as the <quote>Giver of every good <lb/>thing.</quote> (Not her
                  words, of course.) Her <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Gaskell_Holland">Aunt Liz=<lb
                        break="no"/>=zy</persName> is coming here soon, and tonight I told <lb/>her
                  we should have <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Gaskell_Holland">Aunt
                  Lizzy</persName>here in three <lb/>weeks, if we were all well. <q>But whom must
                     <lb/>we ask to keep us well.</q> (<persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">M.
                     A.</persName>)<q><persName ref="#God">God</persName>.</q> After a <lb/>pause
                  she added <quote>I shall ask <persName ref="#God">God</persName> to keep
                        <lb/><persName ref="#Elizabeth_Gaskell_Holland">Aunt Lizzy</persName> well
                     too.</quote> She went to chapel for <lb/>the first and only time on
                     <date>Christmas day</date>, &amp; <lb/>was I think a little tired, though she
                  likes <lb/>much to talk about it.</p>
               <p>She has picked up all her large letters, <lb/>and can arrange them so as to make
                  Dog <lb/>Cow, Horse. She can say <q><title>The Little Busy Bee</title></q> - <pb
                     n="65"/><lb/>but I do not know if she attaches much <lb/>meaning to the
                  words.</p>
               <p><lb/>Her temper continues liable to the same <lb/>fault obstinacy. In some moods
                  if told to <lb/>do a thing, she remains with her hand pat=<lb break="no"/>=ting her
                  mouth, almost like one stupid; <lb/>it is then so difficult to move her, and it
                  has <lb/>been <hi rend="underline">most</hi> difficult to find a judicious reme<lb
                     break="no"/>dy. I am very sorry to say that after trying <lb/>several, we have
                  been obliged occasionally to give <lb/>a slight whipping. It has been done
                  sorrowfully <lb/>and gently, and has never failed in making <lb/>her more
                  obedient, without producing the <hi rend="underline">least</hi>
                  <lb/>resentful feeling. She is a sweet little creature <lb/>in general; full of
                  good feeling. She would give <lb/>rather too freely to the poor. <q>I love
                        <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">you</persName>, and
                        <lb/><persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName>, &amp; <persName
                        ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, &amp; <persName
                        ref="#Elizabeth_Barlow_household">Elizabeth</persName>, &amp; <persName
                        ref="#Fanny_household">Fanny</persName>, and poor <pb n="66"
                     /><lb/>people.</q>
                  <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">William</persName> says he fears I excite her
                     sensi=<lb break="no"/>=bilities too much; I hope not, for I should <lb/>dread
                  it as much as he can do. I have no <lb/>time to write about our dear little
                     <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> tonight. <lb/>I must devote my
                  next <q><hi rend="underline">chapter</hi></q> to her. In <lb/>the mean time I may
                  just mention that <lb/>the two dear little sisters seem very fond <lb/>of each
                  other. May God ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s them both, <lb/>and preserve them to us. <!-- possible half-quotation here. -->Neverthele<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s not <lb/>my will be done, <choice>
                     <reg>but</reg>
                     <sic>by</sic>
                  </choice> thine O <persName ref="#God">Lord</persName>. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="9">
               <head>Entry 9</head>
               <dateline>April 8, 1838</dateline>
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  3 and a half; <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, aged 14 months</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Two weeks since the previous entry.</head>
               <head>Length of Entry: Four and two halves handwritten pages.</head>
               <p>The ninth entry draws comparisons between the two daughters, and is particularly
                  concerned with health, and again, with the possibility of loss. <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> opens the entry by
                  recounting her fright at <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s
                  recent <quote>attack of croup,</quote> which likely occurred only days after the
                  previous entry. This illness was deeply significant for <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>; it forms the primary
                  substance of a contemporaneous letter, dated <date when="1838-03-30">March 30,
                     1838</date> to <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Gaskell_Holland">Eliza (Aunt Lizzy)
                     Gaskell</persName>, <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">William Gaskell</persName>’s
                  then unmarried sister, and one of <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>’s most frequent early correspondents. Gaskell also comments
                  in both sources (diary and letter) about the death of <persName
                     ref="#Edward_Deane">Eddy Deane</persName>, whose father, <persName
                     ref="#Richard_Deane">Dr. Richard Deane</persName>, was <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s uncle <persName
                     ref="#Peter_Holland">Peter Holland</persName>’s partner in
                     <placeName ref="#Knutsford">Knutsford</placeName>. <persName ref="#Edward_Deane">Eddy
                     Deane</persName> was nine months older than <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> and had been ill with croup the same night as <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> and died four days later.
                     G<persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> interjects a
                  prayer for resignation into the account following this story. </p>
               <p>This entry marks another instance of <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName>’s own rereading of her journal. As she turns from recording
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s illness to fulfill
                  her promise of devoting the next <quote>chapter</quote> to <persName
                     ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, she writes <quote>I have been amused on
                     looking at my former writing in this book to perceive the difference between
                     the two little girls.</quote>
                  <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> has done this
                  before, commenting on her own perception of the diary as she rereads it before
                  continuing its composition.</p>
               <p><persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> continues with a
                  description of <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s
                  development, much like those earlier in the diary for <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>. <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell"
                     >Meta</persName> is independent, crawling and pulling herself up, playing and
                  making noise. She is more fretful than <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>, and <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> reasserts her former <quote>rules,</quote> although in
                  Meta’s case, she fears that the servants are spoiling her rather than attending to
                  them. <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> eagerly wants what her sister
                  has, and according to the entry, eats nearly everything she is given as well. The
                  entry ends with a brief comment on the sisters’ relationship, this time worrying
                  that although they get along well, <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> on occasion hurts <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell"
                     >Meta</persName> knowingly. The entry closes with another prayer for their
                  preservation, and a dash, perhaps indicating a hurried closing. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="9">
               <!-- Verification Complete 12/29/19 -->
               <head>
                  <date when="1838-04-08">April 8. Sunday <time>Evening</time>.</date>
               </head>
               <p><lb/>Just a fortnight since I wrote last, <lb/>and since that time I have had a
                  <lb/>sad fright about <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, on
                  last <lb/>Friday but one she had an attack of <lb/>croup about 8 o'clock in the
                  evening. We <lb/>heard a cough like a dog's
                  bark,<!-- Wanted to code this far to show evidence for dating this entry in 1838: Gaskell writes that the previous entry was a fortnight before, indicating that this entry is also from 1838. #mjk-->
                  (she <pb n="67"/><lb/>had had a cold in her head, and had <lb/>seemed pale, and
                  languid all day.) We <lb/>gave her <!--unclear-->24 drops of Ipec: Wine, and
                     <persName ref="#Sam_Gaskell">Sam</persName>
                  <lb/>&amp; <persName ref="#James_Partington">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.
                     Partington</persName> both came. They said <lb/>we had done quite
                  rightly,<!-- comma not in shattock --> and ordered her <lb/>some calomel powders.
                  Of course so much <lb/>medicine, and the nece<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sary confinement <lb/>in the house have made her not so strong, <lb/>and
                  prevented her from going to school, but <lb/>we have reason to be most thankful
                  that <lb/>she is spared to us, and I do earnestly <lb/>and humbly hope that I am
                  truly thank<lb break="no"/>=ful. Poor little <persName ref="#Edward_Deane">Eddy
                     Deane</persName> was taken ill of <lb/>croup on the same night; and died on
                  <lb/>the following Monday. (Oh! may I bring <lb/>myself to a thorough resignation
                  about <pb n="68"/><lb/>the afflictions which <persName ref="#God">God</persName>
                  may see fit <lb/>to send me; and Oh <persName ref="#God">Lord</persName>, while I
                  pray thee <lb/>to preserve my darling children, may I <lb/>not be too much wrapt
                  up in them. Every <lb/>proof of <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>'s delicacy seems to en=<lb break="no"/>=dear her more to
                  me.<!-- missing closing parentheses --></p>
               <p><lb/>when I last wrote in my journal, I was <lb/>stopped by the <choice>
                     <sic>latene<choice>
                           <sic>&#383;</sic>
                           <reg>s</reg>
                        </choice>s</sic>
                     <reg>lateness</reg>
                  </choice> of the hour before <lb/>I had put down any particulars about
                     <lb/><persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>. I have been amused on
                  looking <lb/>at my former writing in this book to <lb/>perceive the difference
                  between the two <lb/>little girls. <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>
                  is far more independent <lb/>than <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> was at her age, which <lb/>I suppose is owing to her
                  having enjoyed <lb/>more uninterrupted good health. She can <lb/>crawl about any
                  where as quickly as many <lb/>children walk, and if the door is open, <pb n="69"
                  /><lb/>she is in the pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sage directly making to=<lb break="no"/>wards the kitchen. She can raise
                  herself by <lb/>any thing on to her feet, but has no idea of <lb/>walking. She
                  will play on the floor for an <lb/>hour at a time in preference to being <unclear
                     unit="word" quantity="1"/><!-- Wilson and Shattock say "nursed" -->
                  <lb/>She has no idea of talking, though she is <lb/>constantly singing and making
                  noises. She <lb/>is very affectionate, but not so sensitive as <lb/><persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">M. A.</persName> was, for instance she does not in
                  the <lb/>least care for being laughed at, but rather <lb/>enjoys a joke. But I am
                  afraid she runs <lb/>some little danger of being spoilt, for nearly <lb/>every one
                  in the house pets her, and she <lb/>is very full of caprices, and sometimes
                  <lb/>gives way to sad little fits of pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sion, if <lb/>she is a little bit affronted by the most <pb n="70"
                  /><lb/>trifling thing. I am sometimes afraid she <lb/>is not checked enough;
                     <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Barlow_household">Elizabeth</persName> (her
                  nurse)<lb/>always says <q>poor thing, it is time enough to <lb/>,begin</q>- This I
                  know is wrong, though I am <lb/>not sure if I act upon my knowledge. <persName
                     ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>
                  <lb/>loves her <persName ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName> so warmly that I think
                  his <lb/>influence may do much towards conquering <lb/>her little pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sions. If he says <q>Naughty little <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell"
                        >Meta</persName></q>
                  <lb/>she sobs as if her heart would break, so of <lb/>course we avoid such a
                  working upon <lb/>her sensibility. She is generous in giving <lb/>a piece of
                  anything she likes, but not <lb/>good in giving up a plaything, and when=<lb break="no"/>ever she sees <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> occupied or a=<lb break="no"/>=mused by anything, that is
                  the very thing <lb/>she wants to have. She wants every eatable <lb/>or drinkable
                  she sees others having, and <lb/>what is more likes them all down to <lb/>rhubarb
                  and magnesia. </p>
               <pb n="71"/>
               <p><lb/>In general the sisters are very kind to one <lb/>another, though sometimes I
                  have been sorry <lb/>to see <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>,
                  without any anger, or any <lb/>apparent bad feeling, hurt little <persName
                     ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, knowing <lb/>that she hurts her. I think
                  it must be from <lb/>the love of power, but of course we try to check <lb/>it. May
                     <persName ref="#God">God</persName> ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s &amp; <hi rend="underline">preserve</hi> them both - </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="10">
               <head>Entry 10</head>
               <dateline>October 14, 1838</dateline>
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  4 years; <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, aged 20 months</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Six months since the previous entry.</head>
               <head>Length of Entry: Two handwritten pages.</head>
               <p>This is the shortest entry in the diary, barely covering two handwritten pages. In
                  the entry which follows, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> states that she had been interrupted when she last wrote,
                  which in part explains the brevity of this entry. <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>’s focus here is on
                  comparing her daughters; <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> once again
                  is described as <quote>much the most energetic</quote> and constantly
                     <quote>busy</quote>, whereas <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell"
                     >Gaskell</persName> worries that <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> is not <quote>industrious</quote> and requires guidance to
                  keep busy. <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> has improved
                  however, and <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> is
                  pleased to see that her former <quote>obstinacy</quote> is growing less frequent.
                  Even as she comments on her daughters’ achievements and cautiously observes their
                  faults, however, <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName>
                  takes on herself the responsibility: <quote>I am afraid I do not set her a good
                     example,</quote> she writes of <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s lack of initiative. In spite of this however, <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> has begun to read and sew, though
                  she is only four years old. The entry ends rather abruptly after <persName
                     ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> asserts that she still
                  ascribes much of <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s
                  behavior to physical complaints; she makes a consistent effort to keep her
                     <quote>quiet, as otherwise she suffers much from exhaustion which shows itself
                     in increased irritability.</quote> Here the entry ends.</p>
               <p>In the interim between this entry and the previous one, <persName
                     ref="#Queen_Victoria">Queen Victoria</persName>’s coronation took place,
                  although there is no indication that the Gaskells were at all involved in the
                  festivities. An event more likely to have affected them was the formation of the
                     <orgName>Anti-Corn Law Association</orgName> in
                     <placeName ref="#Manchester">Manchester</placeName>, which was to become the <orgName>Anti-Corn
                     Law League</orgName> the following year. Two months before this entry,
                     <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> wrote a letter
                  to <persName ref="#William_Howitt">William Howitt</persName> in which she
                  described <placeName ref="#Clopton Hall">Clopton Hall</placeName>,
                  <!-- having heard he was working on a collection, “Visits to Remarkable Places”. He was impressed with her description and included it nearly verbatim in his “Rural Life of England” (1840). check publication facts-->
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="10">
               <!-- Verification complete 12/29/19 -->
               <head>
                  <date when="1838-10-14">October 14 (38) Sunday <time>Evening</time>.</date>
               </head>
               <p><lb/>My dear little girls are both pretty well and <lb/>healthy. How thankful I ought
                  to be; and I <lb/>do feel thankful for the ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sings, I have in <lb/>my children. I hope they are improving <lb/>in
                  every way. <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> has begun since
                  <lb/>her birthday (<date when="1838-09-12">Sep 12</date>) to read and sew, and
                  <lb/>makes pretty good progre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s, especially in the <lb/>working time. I am glad of something that
                  <lb/>will occupy her, for I have some difficulty <pb n="72"/><lb/>in finding her
                  occupation, and she does not <lb/><hi rend="underline">set herself</hi> to any
                  employment. In this respect <lb/>I think <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell"
                     >Meta</persName> will be very different. She is almost <lb/>always busy -
                  sometimes in mischief to be sure, <lb/>but she is much the most energetic of the
                  two <lb/>sisters. I wish very much to make <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>
                  <lb/>industrious; I am afraid I do not set her a <lb/>good example. I try to
                  employ her in making <lb/>candlelighters, printing pictures, counting out
                  <lb/>articles &amp;c, but she is soon tired of any <hi rend="underline">one</hi>
                  <lb/>employment. This must be struggled against <lb/>for I can tell from
                  experience how increasing <lb/>an error this is. In temper and habits of obedience
                  <lb/>I think <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">M. A.</persName> is much
                  improved. She has <lb/>much le<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s frequently those fits of obstinacy <lb/>she used to have. I am so happy
                  to see her <lb/>(general) desire of doing right, and I try <lb/>to exercise her
                  conscience by occasionally <lb/>leaving her to judge if such an action be
                  <lb/>right or not. She is very affectionate, and this <pb n="73"/><lb/>again is a
                  circumstance to be thankful for. <lb/>She has not yet overcome her excitability,
                  and <lb/>we find it nece<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sary <hi rend="strikethrough">for her</hi> to be <hi
                     rend="strikethrough>">kept</hi>keep her very <lb/>quiet, as otherwise she
                  suffers much from <lb/>exhaustion which shows itself in increased ir=<lb
                     break="no"/>=ritability. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <div type="headnote" n="11">
               <head>Entry 11</head>
               <dateline>October 28, 1838</dateline>
               <head>Children's Ages: <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>, aged
                  four years; <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, aged nearly 21
                  months</head>
               <head>Elapsed Time: Two weeks since the previous entry.</head>
               <head>Length of Entry: Four handwritten pages.</head>
               <p>The final entry in the diary is still quite brief, although at the outset
                     <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> states that she
                  intends to <quote>make up for</quote> having been interrupted in the previous
                  entry. She continues to worry about <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>’s health, and writes that they are traveling to
                     <placeName ref="#Prospect Hill">Prospect Hill</placeName>, the home of a relative of <persName
                     ref="#Wm_Gaskell">William</persName>’s, south of
                     <placeName ref="#Warrington">Warrington</placeName>, on the recommendation of William’s brother,
                     <persName ref="#Sam_Gaskell">Sam Gaskell</persName>, who was a physician and
                  seems to have been a frequent purveyor of medical advice to the family. <persName
                     ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> is progressing in other respects,
                  as well, and has begun to have regular lessons at home in reading and sewing.
                     <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> prays for
                  patience in regulating her temper during these lessons. While she applauds
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>’s sympathy for others,
                  she is still concerned about what she believes is a lack of perseverance.
                     <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, however, is generous, walked at
                  18 months, and is very energetic, even passionate at times. Just before closing,
                     <persName ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Gaskell</persName> mentions that
                     <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> has begun to eat
                     <quote>animal food</quote> now that she is four years old. The entry closes, as
                  most do, with a prayer, <quote>May God bless both my dear children.</quote>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry" n="11">
               <!-- Transcription Verified: 12/29/2019 -->
               <head>
                  <date when="1838-10-28">Oct. 28. Sunday <time>Evening</time>.</date>
               </head>
               <p><lb/>I was interrupted when I last wrote, but I shall <lb/>try and make up for it
                  tonight. <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName> and I <lb/>are
                  going in <add type="insertion" place="above">a</add> day to <placeName
                     ref="#Prospect Hill">Prospect Hill</placeName>, on account of <lb/>her health;
                  she has grown very much lately, and <lb/>her <persName ref="#Sam_Gaskell">Uncle
                     Sam</persName> thinks it desirable for her to have a <lb/>little change of air
                  before winter sets in. I hope <lb/>it will do her good, but there are so many
                  things <lb/>in another person's house that one cannot regulate <lb/>(meals,
                  temperature &amp;c) that I feel a little anxious. <lb/>I think I did not mention
                  in my last account <lb/>that, since she was four years old (<date
                     when="1838-09-12">Sep 12</date>) she has <pb n="74"/><lb/>begun to have regular
                  little le<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sons; before that time <lb/>indeed she had learnt her letters, partly in
                  play.- <lb/>She began with one word a day, in <q><persName
                        ref="#Elizabeth_Stevenson_Gaskell">Mama</persName>'s le<choice>
                        <sic>&#383;</sic>
                        <reg>s</reg>
                     </choice>sons,</q>
                  <lb/>but as of course it was one <hi rend="underline">new</hi> word, she now
                  <lb/>sometimes reads nearly a line. She seems to like <lb/>it and takes pains.
                  Sometimes in her sewing <lb/>le<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sons (of six stitches in seaming). I fear I am not <lb/>patient enough.
                  Oh <persName ref="#God">God</persName>, in whose hands are all <lb/>hearts make me
                  more even-tempered. With her <lb/>I do try a great deal, but Oh my <persName
                     ref="#God">Father</persName> help me <lb/>to regulate my impatient temper
                  better!</p>
               <p><lb/>She is a most sympathetic little thing. She tries <lb/>so to comfort me if
                  she sees me looking sad, <lb/>or thinks that anything has happened to dis=<lb
                     break="no"/>=comfort me. <space type="long"/>Her great faults are unaccountable
                  <lb/>fits of obstinacy; which are I hope diminishing <lb/>and a want of
                  perseverance and depend<choice>
                     <reg>e</reg>
                     <sic>a</sic>
                  </choice>nce <lb/>upon <unclear unit="word" quantity="1"
                     ><!-- 2 earlier editions both state others -->others</unclear> as to her
                  occupations and amuse=<lb break="no"/>=ments. I have begun to teach her a little
                  prayer <lb/>morning and night, merely a few words, <pb n="75"/><lb/>of
                  thanksgiving and ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sing. I am not sure <lb/>that she attaches much devotional feeling to
                  this <lb/>observance, but I thought it desirable to lead her <lb/>to something
                  beyond the visible and material, and <lb/>some day I hope more interest will be
                  shown as <unclear resp="Shattock_and_Wilson"
                     ><!-- crossbar of t has nearly disappeared -->to</unclear>
                  <lb/>the <persName ref="#God">Being</persName> to whom they are addre<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sed. She also <lb/>comes in every morning, while her <persName
                     ref="#Wm_Gaskell">Papa</persName> reads from <lb/><title resp="Wilson_Shattock"
                     >Doddindge's Expositor</title> and prays. I sometimes fear <lb/>this service is
                  too long for her, but I think she likes <lb/>coming in, though at first we had a
                  great strug=<lb break="no"/>gle, owing I think to a sort of nervous shyne<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s. <lb/><persName ref="#God">God</persName> ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s and preserve my darling <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName>!</p><p><lb/>As to dear little <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName>, she is
                  totally different <lb/>from <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland"
                     >Marianne</persName> though very like her in person. <lb/>She is a more popular
                  character: very lively, <lb/>enjoying a joke, always busy for herself; but
                  <lb/>she is pa<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sionate and wilful, though less so I <lb/>think than she was. She is a
                  most generous <pb n="76"/><lb/>little creature, always ready to give away
                  eatables. <lb/>Not <hi rend="underline">so</hi> generous as to her
                  <!-- hyphen my addition, previous versions one word -->play-things, but often very
                  <lb/>good about that. She has many engaging ways, <lb/>ki<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>sing if she thinks she has offended or hurt in <lb/>any way. She is very
                  backward in her talking, - <lb/>Tata being the only word she can say - with an
                  <lb/>attempt at <q>please</q>. But she understands and notices <lb/>every word
                  that is spoken before her, and makes <lb/>herself understood too by signs and
                  noises. She <lb/>has walked this two months, being a very good <lb/>walker at 18
                  months. She has just cut her last <lb/>eye-tooth, and I am glad that trial is over
                  for <lb/>her, poor darling, though she has not suffered <lb/>much to what many
                  children do. <persName ref="#MA_Gaskell_Holland">Marianne</persName>
                  <lb/>has within this fortnight begun to have a little <lb/>animal food, but we
                  keep <persName ref="#Meta_Gaskell">Meta</persName> to the old <lb/>plain diet. May
                     <persName ref="#God">God</persName> ble<choice>
                     <sic>&#383;</sic>
                     <reg>s</reg>
                  </choice>s both my dear children.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
